He will be a staff for the righteous with which for them to stand and not to fall and he will be the light of the
Nations and the hope of those whose hearts are troubled all who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship him and they will praise and
Bless and celebrate with song the Lord of spirits first Enoch chapter 48 verses 4 through 5
The modern world doesn't acknowledge but is nevertheless haunted by spirits angels demons and
saints. In our time many yearn to break free of the prison of a flat secular
materialism, to see and to know reality as it truly is. What is this spiritual
reality like? How do we engage with it well? How do we permeate everyday life
with spiritual presence? Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Steven
Damick and Father Steven DeYoung host this live call in show focused on
Enchantment in creation the union of the seen and unseen
as made by God and experienced by mankind throughout history. Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Hey, what's up, Dragon Slayers and Giant Killers? You're listening to the 145th episode of this
here Lord of Spirits podcast. I'm Father Andrew Stephen Daymack and scunced in the palace of
podcasting in Raleigh, North Kackalackie. And with me is Father Stephen DeYoung,
thyroid deep in the fetid swamps of Lafayette, Louisiana.
Yeah. Father Andrew, I thought you were dead.
He says he's...
I've been watching a lot of 80s action movies, so that's I'm going to greet everyone from
now on.
Nice.
I mean, I do feel like 80s action movies, not to mention 80s sitcoms and TV dramas often
revolved around someone not being dead.
Yes.
Yeah.
It's a trope that you can get.
The beginning of every Arnold Schwarzenegger movie, right?
Yeah.
I thought you were dead.
Yeah, exactly.
So we are live, meaning that starting in the second half, Mike Florida Manne
again is going to be taking your calls.
I have to say everybody, this episode actually was canceled.
This episode was canceled because there were big storms
that ripped through Northwestern Indiana
and took out power for about 300,000 people in that region.
Apparently it is the biggest power outage
they've ever had in recorded history.
But it also took out power
for the ancient faith radio headquarters
in Chesterton, Indiana,
But, through the heroic efforts of sci-
Simon and Mike, Simon particularly, who drove all the way to South Bend, Indiana, home of,
I don't know, is that a bend of a river?
Is that what's going on there?
No.
Yeah, Notre Dame.
That is true.
There's also that university there.
And Elkhart is somewhere nearby.
That's the band instrument capital of the world.
And also home to the RV Hall of Fame.
Have you ever been there to the RV Hall of Fame, Father Stephen?
No.
I have driven by it.
actually gone inside.
But anyway, they are running on generators right now.
Actually, there's two generators powering the servers and the studio equipment,
even though they don't have any air conditioning.
So hurrah, hurrah, hurrah for Chesterton HQ.
I mean, amazing guys. Good job. Good job.
Because of the cancellation and uncancellation, just so that, you know,
the audience is fair to you as everyone on social media always tries to be.
to be.
Father Andrew is far less prepared than usual.
That is true.
I am not because I am unprepared as usual.
But the thing that you always predicted would happen did finally happen, which is that you
were canceled.
Sort of.
But it means you were uncanceled because of pressure from special interest groups.
Big generator, I guess.
That's right.
Exactly.
So anyway, so yes, well.
Welcome, everybody. I almost got to stay home tonight. And then they did amazing things up
there in Indiana, the poor man's Ohio. So here we are. Okay, so let's get on with it.
So for almost six years now, I mean, can you believe it that this podcast within just a
few weeks is going to be six years old? For almost six years now, this podcast has been
accused many times, many times of just serving up warmed overwork from a prominent
biblical scholar. After all of that, all that giant lore and that fallen angel stuff
could not.
But be the work of one man. Why isn't he being credited in every episode?
So tonight we reveal, finally, who that man is.
When we finally give him the credit he deserves.
Who is it, Father Stephen? Who is that man?
TV's Bob Yooker.
That was not in the notes.
This show is just a remake of Mr. Belvedere.
And none of you figured it out that brings me back a lot
That was a great show actually or at least I remember it as a great show. I have not watched it in
40 years, but I remember our new arrival. Life is more than mere survival
Yeah, yeah
So is there anyone besides Bob Yooker that we've been you know, I have to say by the way with a name like Yooker
He must be from Ohio because Yooker is like the
It is the Ohio game when you cross the borders of Ohio
They give you a deck of Euker cards and you're required to learn to play it or else they deport you to
Indiana probably actually
Did you know that from Ohio? Yes, that would be the way that would be the direction. That's right. That's right
They would support you. Yep. Yep
People from Michigan and Mars and Mars and Melbourne ours. I don't know what I mean. Maybe it's Mars Vermont
want.
Yeah. Utah, Toronto. Well, it's someone from North Carolina. I see you, North Carolina.
And Georgia, United States. What is this? The end of Romper Room now? What's going on?
Yeah, yeah. What's that thing? Wow, it's all, it's 80s night tonight on Lurie Pierce podcast.
I see you and Tom and that's right. Yeah, someone said that.
can't believe that you almost got canceled by the weather. That wasn't on you. But the thing is,
is that it wasn't Father Stephen's weather this time. Yes, that's what's amazing. It wasn't that
a hurricane whipped through here. It was that, yeah, it whipped through Indiana. Oh, hey,
Cape Breton Island. Hello, Virginia. Manitoba, Mammoth Lake, California. Is that your part
part of your California, Father Stephen.
Uh, man, we have a serve someone.
from Serbia, someone from west of Charlotte. Hey, west of Charlotte, are you in Gastonia
or maybe Shelby, one of my favorite car-tipping towns? I'm from west of Charlotte. And a bit
south as well. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. So hello, everybody. We're glad to have you here
at the end of all things.
Mainland China is west of Charlotte, technically.
But don't leave us. So yeah, the person is St. Irenaeus. That's the whole that's the whole bit. It is St. Irenaeus
That's right. Yeah, and and we should say it's it's
It's not just St. Irenaeus, but that's who we're talking about tonight. That's it
Yes, if we can twist Father Stephen's arm, which is difficult because he's got a big arm
We might even do more than one episode on early church fathers from whom we have
boldly brazenly
bald facently
Stolen stolen not stoned stolen so many things that we see on this podcast plagiarism left and right
That's why
Yeah, I see all these people online they say we never quote the church fathers that we plagiarize modern scholarship
This is the opposite of true. We plagiarize the church fathers, and we never quote modern scholarship indeed indeed if that correct
Yes, and second, Irenaeus is a big one in terms of our plagiarism, and you will be seeing
that tonight.
I have always given you the audience the respect of assuming that, you know, you would say
things on the show, and you would go and, you know, hey, I don't know, read the church
trodders read the Bible and say, oh hey, I see what they were saying, here it is.
Right. Yeah. So, yeah, that's why we plagiarize so freely from Church Fathers.
I mean, that's why we get so many, we're not making this up moments.
Well, out of copyright. I mean, I feel like the Church Fathers ideas are now in public domain.
Yes. Yes. Well, this is, this is something I've actually said for a long time, like
Like, any idea...
like in my books or anything or podcast or talks or anything any ideas that are
truly unique to me are wrong probably wrong yeah it should be disregarded
it's right the only stuff you should pay attention to is the stuff I'm saying
that has already been said in the end and the other thing I think is worth
pointing out because it's it's a funny thing you know they say you should
never read your own press right but I have nothing else to do but but like
I guess I'll give him
a bunch of kids in a family of stuff. Occasionally I read people saying stuff like, they assert
simply as this is the case, stuff that's their opinions or whatever. And it's like, I don't
think we've ever rapped hardly any of the things that they would like to point out
in the wrapper of, and this is the dogmatic tradition of the Orthodox church. Like for
instance, that the only way you can read this biblical passage is in this one way.
In fact, we've gone on and on about how that's a ridiculous way to read the Bible
to begin with.
with. Yes, but that would require people listening to more than clips. That is true. Yeah, three
cheers for Thelogumana. There is. Yeah, you have to follow the circular reasoning. The
circular reasoning is their show is bad. I'm not going to listen to it. I listened to this
short clip, see how bad it is. Therefore, I'm not going to listen to it. Alas. But
But all of those of you who have tuned in tonight, you know the secret are not those people.
Yes, right, you know, especially if you're listening live unless someone has clipped to this. Oh
We got a comment actually. This is a completely completely irrelevant to the the show
But someone asking can you help a find an English-speaking orthodox church in Toronto?
St. George and Richmond Hill is quite good
Commenter actually it is multilingual, but they use mainly English and it's a great wonderful loving community
And the food is very very good. I just want to add that there. So
Yep. Yep. Okay now
we're a church finder. Okay. We're a full service podcast. Okay. You're, you're, you're
the squeegee guy, man. Okay. Who is St. Irenaeus? Who is the people? What is with? No. Um,
So yes, St. Irenaeus, real briefly here, who is, right, we're not, we're obviously
we're not.
Cards on the table this episode is not just hey, it's the St. Irenaeus episode
We're gonna be talking about a particular work of St. Irenaeus. Yes, that is true. And so
Little bit of brief biography to sort of frame, you know for those who don't know St. Irenaeus
Was Greek
He was born in Smyrna
He was from a Christian family he's living
of the second century, so the 100s. So he's one of the probably second generation of people
being born into Christian families that are already Christian. He was a disciple of Saint
St. Polycarp, when St. Polycarp was Bishop of Smyrna.
And Polycarp was a dis...
disciple of St. John the Apostle, which means that Irenaeus is just two generations removed
from the Apostles.
Right.
He is sort of a spiritual grandson of St. John.
And when we say he's a disciple, we don't just mean, oh, St. Paulicarp was the bishop
of his city, but St. Irenaeus, when you read his works, he talks about, you know,
he mentions St. Paulicarp, he mentions other people in the area who had heard St. John
preach and who
he listened to talk about and discourse about particular things.
So he's a disciple of the sense that he was a student of them,
like he learned from them, right?
These things.
He later, under circumstances that we don't know for sure,
moved to what was called at the time, Lugdunham.
Sounds to me like it's in Scotland,
but it's not, it was in Gaul.
Uh...
AKA
France, which had a couple hundred years before that been divided into three parts.
But as one guy, that city is more well known as Leon Leon.
Yeah.
And that's the later name all the way to the present day.
We hence why he's referred to a Saint Irenaeus of Leon.
He became the second Bishop of Leon.
in or around AD 177, because the previous bishop, the first bishop of the city, St.
Pothinus, was martyred by Marcus Aurelius. Good old Mark. I know the guy that people
love to quote in memes as like the... Yeah, yeah. Stoicism. That's right. I mean,
there's a lot of Christians, you guys. And one of the most virulent persecutors of Christian.
And Kudos to Ridley Scott, by the way, right, because, you know, some of you may be remembering
Gladiator, that American classic, where Marcus Aurelius is like the good guy emperor, you
know, at the beginning, and then his son, Commodus is a loon.
His son, Commodus was a loon.
That is absolutely the case.
In my house we call him commode.
Yeah, so, but originally, the original cut of that film, Ridley Scott had filmed scenes
of both father and son throwing Christians to wild animals in the Colosseum, and he had
acknowledged the Christian persecutions under those emperors, but the studio cut those
scenes out for time.
Wow.
So.
theatrical cut of gladiator has no mention of Christianity in it. Fun fact for today.
But Marcus Aurelius, one of his persecutions, was in Gaul in the region around Lyon, and
the bishop was martyred as part of that, and that's when St. Irenaeus, who had been
been previously a priest, a presbyter there, what?
consecrated as bishop. Yeah. And there is a tradition, I mean, he's traditionally
referred to as a higher martyr, although like if you look up, if you look up
academic comments on that, they'll all say, oh, the tradition that he was a
higher martyr is very late, blah, blah, blah. But the church does remember him as
a higher martyr. But the earliest known attestations we have to that, I
can't remember where they're, when they're from, but it's definitely later
than, you know, they're not from the second century, they're no it's very
Yeah, yeah, like even even Eusebius doesn't have how he died. Hmm. Yeah, there's no comment either way, right?
But there's but it's like I mentioned him doing something in 191. I think writing a letter. Yeah, there's a Bishop of Rome in 191
and then Eusebius just doesn't mention him again. So yeah, it's not it's not that it's unbelievable. I mean, there's a lot of Christians being killed at this
this period and his predecessor was bartered. Yeah, Bishop's bishops are big.
you know, so if the church remembers him as being martyred,
I see no reason not to just accept that.
Yeah, yeah.
Well, we'll get to that here in a minute.
Yes, yes.
That whole idea.
Yeah, so if any of you need any more reasons to dislike Calvinism,
I can't imagine anyone in our audience needs any more reasons
to dislike Calvinism, but...
Uh, uh, say your.
Today's relics were pretty much destroyed by Huguenots, by French Calvinists.
If you really are looking for more reasons to dislike Calvinism, to hate Calvinism, good
old Doc Jenkins' book, Calvin's Tormentors, Calvin's Tormentors will give you a whole
new series of ways to dislike Calvin.
Yeah.
So put that out there.
What I say they destroy
his relics like they destroyed and burned down the ancient church in which his relics were kept.
Right. Right. Like so we're talking like insane madness level like of desecration.
And people wonder why the French crown had such a problem with the Huguenots and wiped them all out.
Yeah. But I imagine there's some correct for net French pronunciation of Huguenot.
Like, they weren't the sailors on the Hugo.
right after all but uh but yeah so they did that there's there is potentially one portion of his
relics that have survived so here's a fun fact that's there are two skull fragments and a heel bone
hmm that different shirt post this is post-predicent
Reformation, post-counter-Reformation, that Roman Catholic churches in France say are
portions of his relics that survived the destruction. They did carbon dating on them, and the two
skull fragments are from the medieval period, according to the carbon dating. But the
the heel bone dated to the second century.
So that the good you bone is potentially a surviving relic of St. Irenaeus. Yeah, I mean the good thing about I
Don't want to say the good thing the the the mild consolation
That we can get from some of those reformation
destructions of relics is that in in a number of cases, of course the relics had been divided before
these different iconoclastic Protestant groups got hold of them and
Bits were taken to other places. So
One of the areas that, of course, that this was really, really bad was in the United Kingdom.
What is now the United Kingdom?
Lots and lots of relics were destroyed.
But in a number of cases, before King Henry VIII, blasted be his name, got hold of these
relics.
Often parts were taken to the continent and enshrined in churches there.
And so in some cases, what's happened is actually relics that were in Western Europe
somewhere.
have now come back in little particles to the UK. So for instance, I got to venerate a relic of
Saint Mildred of Thanet in Thanet, but it was a relic that had made its way to the continent and
then came back. And there's various relics like that in the UK. And so it's entirely possible that,
as you said, that there could be this this relic of Saint Irenaeus that exists.
There are significant relics of Saint Martin of Tours here in Louisiana.
Yeah, I think actually Saint Martin's Shrine
is pretty together from what I, someone told me that they actually venerated him in tours.
So that's great. That's really good to know. I mean, these pilgrimages are really things
that are important to me. I love to go to St. St. John's and sing and, you know, make the
local process and some barista. Yeah, the dancing especially is I think
more than the singing. When you're happy, you're happy.
And you are after all, a song and dance man.
I am a fun-and-dance man that is completely true
so
Yeah, so the the most the most famous work of
St. Irenaeus is
Against heresies or at versus heresies because if you write in Latin you sound smarter
But he was writing in Greek though, right it's kind of
funny that the the names that are well because we don't have a
complete Greek copy. Yeah, the complete copy we have is in
Latin. And so that's why it and the reason it and that brings
us to why it's the most famous. It's not the most famous
because it's like uniformly considered the best thing he
ever wrote or anything. It's the most famous because for most
of history, it's the only thing we had.
True and but also like like, you know, even apart from
Um, like if you've never read, uh, against heresies, dear listeners, um, it is, I mean,
it exactly what it, what it says on the, on the label, it's, it's, it's in some ways like,
you know, uh, warning self promotion coming some ways my book orthodoxy and heterodoxy
is modeled on that kind of thing.
Like it's a big list in some ways of all these different doctrines and religious
groups.
And then he critiques saying all protestants and Roman Catholics are here.
paratix people. That's what Father Andrew just said.
And I'm not not saying that. And I'm not disagreeing.
And then another like another text that's similar is by Saint Epiphanios of Sonamis, which is
called the Panadion, which means the bread box, which I love that. But one of the reasons
why it's so famous is not just because for people who are interested in the history
of doctrine or whatever, but because...
In a lot of ways, it's the only written evidence we have of what the teachings and the leaders
of some of these ancient, particularly Gnostic groups, what they actually were, right?
So he actually has a record of a lot of this stuff in his text now while he's, you know,
writing polemic against it.
But that's one of the reasons it's actually a really valuable historical document.
And of course, people will argue with him and they'll say, oh, that's not what
they really believe or taught.
But in some cases, his is the only testimony we have to it.
So it's like, well, if he's wrong, then we just don't know, you know, which I guess is possible.
But yeah, it's a really, really kind of, like I said, it's an important historical document
describing the religious scene in his, in his, in his day there in the Roman Empire,
you know, in the Western Roman Empire and Gaul. So fascinating.
Yeah, in the area around Rome. Yeah.
I mean, it can be very difficult to read at points, especially if you don't have the,
the, you know, sort of the theological.
context of a lot of what he's talking about. But it's really kind
of, I don't know, fun in a way to read against terraces, you
know, that's why orthodoxy and heterodoxy is so fun. I made
it fun on purpose, because I'm a song and dance man. As I think
of that book, I think of just fun. The, the, yeah, so that
but that, like I said, that was not to denigrate it
Anyway, it's a great work.
Yes, just.
It was like I said, it was the only thing we had from him for most of history.
Um, the, uh, we know of, we have the titles of a whole bunch of things he wrote.
Yep.
Uh, they just haven't survived.
Yep, or haven't been dug up.
And one of those things that we had the title of, but we, uh, didn't have for
most of history, was a work called On the Apostolic Preaching.
Yeah, and or demonstration of the apostolic preaching. Yes. Yes demonstration. I love that one
I mean as most of these texts have no actual titles
Yeah, or or the title is like a page long
Right well a lot of them are just so okay, so the titling is actually important to this in terms of genre
So what are the points?
Listeners have heard me make many times, like when I talk about St. Paul's epistles,
is that they're not theological treatises, right? They're epistles and that's a different genre.
There was such a thing as a philosophical or theological treatise.
Philo wrote them a hundred years before St. Paul lived, right?
So St. Paul could have written them.
So the way those are typically titled, starting in terms of what we still have with Aristotle,
Aristotle it probably goes back to at least play dough and maybe
even before that, we just don't have a lot of that stuff, is in Greek, peri and then the topic.
Yeah, on that gets translated to English is on whatever. Yeah, although it's literally about
like perimeter. Well, or concerning. Yeah, concerning. Yeah. Yeah. But typically just
for shorthand, right? So aerostals on the parts of animals, on the right. Think of
Uh, uh, origin origins, most well-known work.
The Greek title is Perry Arkon on first principles.
Origins on origins.
Yes.
Yeah.
And then in Latin, and then in Latin, this gets, you know,
translated with the word day, which means of literally.
So like, for instance, St.
Athanasius is famous work, not written in Latin, you know, day in
kind of not connazione, right? Yeah. On the incarnate.
So, yeah, so that's, but that tells you the genre. So he is writing this as a theological
treatise, right? And that makes it a different genre than against heresies, right? Against
Terracies is a polemical document. He's arguing against another position. Whereas
in on the apostolic preaching, he's presenting a positive position. He's
making a positive case. He's not attacking a heresy. He's presenting the
truth. He's laying it out. He's saying like, like, like, here's a manual. Like
he's, that's what he's trying to do. He's actually trying to set it all out.
And if you're not sent, you have to be sensitive to that difference
rhetorically. This is a big place where people's reading
of church fathers go wrong. This is a huge place where people's readings of St. Augustine go wrong.
Right? Because St. Augustine wrote both kinds of works. And if you're not sensitive to the fact
that when he's writing against the Pelagians in a polemic work, that's different than his
is on faith, hope and love,
where he's making a positive case of describing virtue.
Those are gonna be very...
rhetorically different. Yeah, I think the big difference is, like, if you're writing a letter
to someone, you're trying to apply things to them in particular, you're not trying to set out,
you know, like if, like if I text one of my sons and say, you know, make sure you do the dishes
today. It's, you know, it's a moral exhortation, right? It's not about, and let me define to
you what it means to be hardworking and industrious and
gives 12 examples, you know, like that's not what I'm doing and it's very much application.
That doesn't mean that you can't derive some of that kind of stuff from a shorter, you know,
or more directed personal message like that.
But it doesn't mean that you should take it as being a whole system.
Yes.
And also, in the same way, if you take a clip, not that this has ever happened
to me, for example, but you take a clip of someone criticizing someone else's position.
position. Yeah. But you pull out the clip so that you don't know that there even is another
position or what that position is. So you don't have that context. And then you try
to present what was said as being, Oh, this is a positive statement. Yes. Of this person's
position. Right. This is what happens to say to Guston all the time. Man, we're picking
on Calvinists tonight, but this is what Calvinists do with St. Augustine's anti-Pelagian writings.
They take arguments who is making against Pelagians and present them as if he's just sitting there writing about his own personal position
Yeah, or like those are two different things one of my favorites. What one of my favorites is how you know like we have said
repeating the church fathers on this podcast that
Christ's humanity
becomes uncreated because it's divinized because he's God and
And there is at least one person, maybe several.
know. It depends on how many retweets there have been saying that that means they're saying that
Christ's flesh is infinite, right? Like, these are not the same thing, people. These are not the
same thing. You know, it's embedded with an old... And by the way, there are ways in which Christ's
flesh is infinite. And there are ways in which it's not. See, again, context. Yeah.
Yeah. In one way, in a certain sense, it, you know, so I could get
you a way in which Christ's flesh is infinite. You can consecrate an infinite
amount of the Eucharist. Yes, that is true. So in that sense, limit, right? There is
not a limit on the amount of the body of Christ that can exist at a given point
in time. But anyway, yeah, that's yeah. So these contextual things and these
rhetorical they are incredibly
important, right? And one of the, one of the major things we've
lost in the modern world is any sense of rhetoric, right? Any
sense of, of rhetoric. And this comes out all over the place.
Right? There's, there's sort of no attempt to do any kind of
rhetorical analysis and try and figure out, because we're in
it, we're in a culture that fundamentally doesn't care
what people mean. Yeah. Right? Especially people who we're
opposed to, in some sense, for some reason, we don't care what
they mean. We just care about what we can do with the words
they say. Yeah, it's just they're exploiting you, Father
Stephen. Right? It doesn't matter what the candidate from
the other political party meant. I've got a clip of him
saying this and it sounds bad. That's what's important.
right? Yeah. But so, especially with the church fathers, we're trying to understand what they're
saying, what they have to teach us and what they're saying. And a big part of being able to do that
and determine that is rhetorical analysis, understanding the context in which they're
saying it and the genre of the text we're reading it from. So again, you don't read on
on the episode.
preaching and against heresies the same way. Against heresies is a criticism of
false belief, right, and on the apostolic preaching is just a positive
presentation of the true theology from St. Ernest. And that's the text we're
going to be talking about tonight if you haven't figured that out yet. And as
As I mentioned, this is a text we...
didn't have for most of history.
Yeah, so he wrote it and then we knew about it. We had the title.
Yeah, when is what is the last mention of it in the early,
you know, back in the day? I know you CBS has it on his list
of writings. You see me some Caesarea. That's fourth, fourth
century. I'm not sure if it's in St.
Proteus the Great's library list from Cuxat and Opal or not.
Um, but, uh, yeah, so we didn't, we knew there was, he had written a thing called that, but
we didn't have a copy until 1904.
That's pretty recent in terms of Christian.
Yes.
It's like last week.
A copy was found in 1904 in a very ancient Armenian cathedral.
Yeah.
Thank you for watching, and I'll see you in the next video.
And for those who don't know, Armenia has some of the oldest church buildings in the world.
Yeah, I mean it was the first Christian nation, officially Christian nation.
Christianity became Lyset there before in the Roman Empire.
And they were doing renovations around the altar.
And they found a cache of texts in old Armenian translation.
translation.
One of which was St. Irenaeus on the Apostolic preaching.
Yep, so this is the only language we have it in.
Yes, it's the only copy.
Yeah, yeah.
It's the only copy we have.
Now, you may be wondering,
well, first of all, you know,
how do we even know that's the real one?
And secondly, if it's in Armenian,
And how do we know how close it is or isn't to
what St. Irenaeus would have written in Greek. Both of which are valid questions.
Yeah. Well, and I mean, I'll say, you know, kids, if you don't have a copy of this, there
is a lovely edition that was published by St. Vladimir's Seminary Press. Not too
long ago, I'm looking at my copy here, 1997. And it was translated by Father John Bear,
who I don't know was.
was he the Dean of St. Vlad's at the time? I can't recall. But anyway, he was he was at St.
Vlad's at the time. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Making making fun of me for my wedding registry. But
anyway, good. And true true story. And it has a really good introduction in it in which he he
really analyzes the history of the text itself. It's really quite fascinating. And one of the
One of the things that he says is, maybe this is where you're going, is that the arm.
Armenian is written in such a way that it's sort of this woodenly literal translation of
Greek, like it's not sort of really natural sounding Armenian. And because of that, they're
actually able to pretty believably reconstruct what the Greek would have been.
Yeah.
And they also, we also have against heresies and old Armenian.
Mm.
There you go.
So we have
that for comparison.
And I think as I recall, I mean, it's been a little bit since I
read the introduction. But as I recall, there's a lot of a lot
of similarity between the two translations in terms of wording
and stuff with a suggestion that they were done by the same
person or maybe the same school of translators, which makes it
even easier to kind of reconstruct, you know what it
might have been. And so as such, I mean, as you're
reading
text as Father John Bear translated it. And actually the apparatus is great in this. This
is one of the best books in terms of a translation in terms if you want to kind of look underneath
the hood a little bit. He'll often give you a Greek word in parentheses after, you know,
something in particular. And it's not because that's in the original. It's because there's
really good reason to believe that that is the original Greek term.
That's what they're translating. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. With key terms sort of key theological terms
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. And so if you've never, if you've never looked at it, and so, you know, we present to you the title is on the Apostolic preaching, that this is him making a positive presentation. This is the teaching of the apostles.
This is what the apostles preached. Your assumption might be if you've never looked at it.
that, oh, he's going to be sort of pulling together quotes from, like, St. Paul and, like,
the Gospels and, like, sort of summarizing the New Testament. And you would be wrong.
Yeah.
100% wrong.
It's wild. It's like, it's basically, basically, his book is about reading the Old Testament
in a Christian way.
So, he is doing what the New Testament does.
Yeah, yeah.
He is reading the Old Testament through the lens of Christ.
So, he is presenting to you the apostolic preaching and apostolic tradition as a way of reading the Scriptures.
There are places, right, where he does at least allude to or use language
That's it for this video.
Thanks for watching.
I'll see you next time.
Bye.
is clearly alluding to New Testament texts, but it's almost always the Johanian literature.
Yeah. Yeah, his spiritual grandfather. He makes a whole bunch of points that are the
same point Saint Paul makes, right? But without making any direct illusion or quotation
of Saint Paul. But when he makes those illusions and uses those phrases, it's the Johanian
literature but really it's
Here's how the apostles read the Old Testament scriptures and taught them.
And one of the places they did that is in the New Testament.
That's why he's sort of doing the same thing the New Testament does.
Yeah, which, which, I mean, this demonstrates for us, punfully intended, this demonstrates
for us what the church fathers fundamentally are doing, right?
They're trying, they're, they're extending the apostolic problem.
project. They're doing the same thing the apostles did.
Yes. They're interpreting and applying the scriptures, right, as the apostles did, but
not just on their own by themselves. So there's this key phrase that St. Irenaeus uses in
both Against Heresies and on the Apostolic preaching. And that is, it's usually translated
in English as the rule of faith. And rule is literally translating the word canon.
Yeah. Yeah.
Kanon in Greek
The rule of faith and what is the rule of faith which he uses interchangeably with the idea of Apostolic tradition. It's a way of reading the scriptures
Hmm. It's a hermeneutic
Yeah, it's an it's an exegetical
Way, I don't want to call it method. Yes, but a way. Yeah, okay, so
So this is important and the reason I'm kind of really pushing
on this is this is important when we get into discussions with our Protestant friends as
Orthodox Christians, the scripture and tradition discussions, right? Because there is this
great tendency that I see for Orthodox Christians to just recycle old Roman Catholic arguments
that are dependent on a Roman Catholic view of scripture and tradition.
Which is not the same as the orthodox view number one. Yeah, so yeah, it it's not
You may think you have a real winning argument against Protestants, but number one
It's not an accurate representation of the orthodox position in contrast and number two
Protestants have heard all of those arguments for 500 years, dude
Yeah, they usually do have a comeback for most of yes, there's there's no point in rehashing
stuff. It's a dance, right, at this point. And, you know, if Orthodox people are going to enter
these apologetic discussions, and we should, we should continue to enter them, right, but we need
to bring something new to the table, right, not just fall on the Protestant side when we're
arguing against the papacy and fall on the Catholic side when we're arguing against
Sola Scriptura, okay? Like, that's not bringing anything new to the dance, right?
And this is a place, right? This is a, one of the fundamental problems with Sola Scriptura is the idea that
or the question
that comes out of it of
Okay, two people read the scriptures in different ways. How do you decide who is right?
How do I decide, you know
Bob says this passage means X, Tom says this passage means Y. How do I know whether I should
believe Bob or Tom? And honestly, the traditional Protestant answer on that is a punt because
the traditional Protestant answer to that is, well, you just have to go by your own
conscience, you know, because yeah, which one which one is persuasive to your conscience?
But that doesn't really answer the question that just says well you can't know you can't really a hundred percent know
Right, but you're gonna stand before God and give an account for it. So you just have to follow your own conscience
Okay
This is the answer to that
Right the answer to that is holy tradition, but not holy tradition in the sense that like
Well, there's all this extra stuff that they didn't write down in the Bible that got handed down by bishops in secret meetings
where they whispered it
their ear, and then hundreds of years later someone proclaimed it publicly.
That's not what tradition is, at least from an Orthodox view.
That's not what Roman Catholics think either, for the record.
That's how it's sometimes caricatured for them.
But it doesn't even vaguely resemble what we think about tradition.
If we understand the rule of faith and we understand holy tradition as this way of
reading the scriptures, then it is the solution to the problem, number one, in
terms of how do we find out who's
Is correct. Well, which one is according to the rule of faith that's been handed down to us from the Apostles, right?
But number two, it makes it impossible to oppose scripture and tradition in that sense
How can the scripture itself be opposed to a way of reading it?
Yeah, the question then is what does it make any sense?
Yeah, right and so you say okay, well, how do we find out this rule of faith?
Well, that's what this St. Irenaeus is doing in this text.
Yeah, he's trying to lay it out for you.
He's laying it out.
He's showing it to us, right?
By going through the Scripture, the Old Testament Scriptures and reading them in the light
of Christ to show us how it's done, right?
And honestly, I would say, like, having just read this book recently, because we decided
of, I don't know, it's been a month maybe or so ago that we decided we were
going to do an episode about this book.
If the only orthodox theology you know is what Irenaeus writes in his book, you're doing
really well actually.
Like, I mean, not that anyone cares what I think, but my opinion is that he does a real
good job.
You know, like it's this, you know, if that's all you've got, you're doing it well.
It's really quite thorough and he doesn't say everything that could be said.
Obviously, there are a lot of other just patristic texts, you know.
But nonetheless, this is a really good encapsulation
Yeah, you know, it's from the second century
So it's gonna take a little bit of contextualization for us people who live, you know, 1900 years later or whatever, but yeah
But this is this is the basics, right? Like this is the gospel. This is right. Yep. There it is. Yeah
so
Relatedly as
We as we conclude our
introductory half here.
I have to comment on something so if you're like me listeners, and I know I am
Then you've had somebody in a discussion probably lots of somebodies at different times
Throw this goofy thing at you
Stay here nails thought that Jesus was 50 when he died
so you can't believe anything he says right sometimes they go further than that
therefore the church fathers don't know anything and just disregard them right
depending on right who it is right and they may do it in a slightly more
sophisticated way than that but that's what it amounts to yeah okay
Thank you.
Sadly, I have even heard some Orthodox people do this in intra-Orthodox disputes where they
have decided they disagree with St. Irenaeus, and they want to justify it by saying, well,
he thought Jesus was 50.
So therefore, nothing he says must be true.
Yes, therefore, yeah.
And then they'll turn around though and quote him at a protestant, right?
Yeah.
that's right after they do that it's like whoa bro you can't
it both ways, right? Like, either he's a reliable witness to the apostolic testimony or he's not,
right? Now, that's not to say that that level of hypocrisy
is true on the Protestant side too, by the way, because a bunch of the same Protestants who
will make that argument about stuff from Saint Irenaeus that they don't like will throw out the
Please?
We'll use St. Irenaeus to say, oh look, St. Irenaeus had all four Gospels, had the four
Gospels, four canonical Gospels in the middle of the second century where they're in a canon
argument.
Yeah, they want to use them when they like what he says.
Yes, whenever he agrees with me, he's right.
Whenever he disagrees, he's wrong.
Yeah.
Right?
That's definitely not scholarship, right?
That's that's that's not even a tenable position, right? Like either either he is an authority on these issues or he isn't
Either he is trustworthy on these issues or he isn't
Okay, yeah
Test that his testimony is
Creditable or it is discredited. That's it. Okay, but what's going on with this whole?
This is gonna be the only place where we tonight
we're really dipping to against heresies,
because that's where this comes from.
Book two.
section 22 of Against Heresies, right? And that's obviously false. It's obviously false. Okay.
So, let's talk about Against Heresies, book two, section 22. So, first of all, one cool
thing in it is that St. Irenaeus says in there that Christ was born in 3 BC.
Where have we heard that before? It's almost like we're not making this stuff up
But also
He is again against heresies is a polemic work
He is criticizing the false beliefs of certain Gnostic sex
There are Gnostic sex who?
we're teaching that. Jesus, his ministry began when he was 30 years old, which we
get in St. Mark's Gospel. St. Mark's Gospel says that Jesus began his public
ministry and he was about 30. There's a vagary word in there, so he might have
been exactly, it wasn't like his 30th birthday, but right, that's around the
time. And they said, which you
You can argue, by the way, based on the synoptic Gospels, that Christ's ministry was only one
year long.
A little less.
He died in the 12th month of his ministry.
And they were asserting this dogmatically, these Gnostic groups, because they were doing
this numerology thing.
They needed his whole life to be 30 years long.
And it's public ministry to be his 30th year because they had like 30 years.
30 emanations. It was this whole thing. Yeah. Yeah. Right. And he died in the 12th month
of his vision is 12. They're doing all these numerological things. Okay. So that's what
St. Irenaeus is criticizing. First of all, St. Irenaeus is not just writing and he's
like, Oh, hey, fun fact. Here's how old Jesus was when he died. Yeah. Right. Right.
So, he is opposing that.
Okay?
Now, how does he oppose that?
Okay, so he opposes that by saying, and his central point, his central positive point over
against that, is that Christ passed through because of his view of the atonement and recapitulation
in the incarnation, that Christ lived through all of the ages of human life.
Hmm.
Meaning...
Infancy childhood young adulthood adulthood and then mature full adulthood. That's the point. He's trying to make. Okay, and
If he had died at 30
Right, he would not have really entered into adulthood
So that's that's the key point. Say Irenaeus is trying to make. Okay
How does he make that?
two ways. Number one, he says, that people like St. Paulicarp and other people who had
heard St. John speak, heard him say that Christ had entered into mature adulthood. He does
not give an exact age in that context. He never gives an exact age, by the way. He
never gives an exact age. But, right, he says that Christ had lived to mature adulthood
and then
He quotes St. John's Gospel.
He quotes the Bible, okay?
The Bible is where he is getting this, where when Christ says that Abraham had seen him,
right?
It's St. John's Gospel.
The Jews say to him, you are not yet fit.
50 years old. How can, how can you have lived in Abraham's time? And so
senior day says, if he was like barely 30, why would they say you are not yet 50 years
old?
Yeah.
This is, that doesn't make sense. Right? That's, you would say you're not yet 50
years old to someone who's
like middle-aged, right? Someone who's clearly not an old man, but also clearly not a young
man, right? Someone who's middle-aged. And therefore, it makes more, then that means,
and again his argument is, therefore, there are several years of ministry after Christ
baptism at around the age of 30 that happened and St. John's gospel testified.
to this. And there were people who St. Irenaeus had met, who had heard St. John speak, who could
verify that. That's what against heresy says. Okay. Now our Protestant friends who like
to quote this, who are who like to refer to that they don't quote it, they reference
it, right? Number one act like he gave the age of 50. He most certainly did not.
He said he was it.
part of the whole argument is that he's not yet 50. Yeah. Okay. So St. Ernest doesn't say
that Jesus was 50 when he died. That's just not true. You haven't read carefully. But
he says he's been laged, right? And you could make a good argument that he's alluding to
him being in his 40s, right? But where? Where do we get more importantly, where do
our Protestant friends who use this argument.
Where did they get that Jesus ministry was three years long? Where does it say in the Bible that Jesus ministry was three?
Yeah, I don't I don't recall on pan that it
Yeah, it's interesting
No, where so the the St. John's Gospel
It's a new day points this out to St. John's Gospel
um, is structured around three cycles of the feast, right? Right. That doesn't necessarily
mean that those are three years in a row. And that's his whole ministry. Yeah. Yeah. Like
there's three, right? Yeah, there's three passovers mentioned in John's gospel. Yes.
Yeah, and only one mention of this optics.
Right, but
When you look at St. John's gospel and you look at his chronology
For example, he has the cleansing of the temple at the beginning of Christ's ministry instead of the end
mmm
So St. John's doing interesting things with chronology. So
What we have here is a case where Protestants
Are some of our Protestant friends
trying to argue, right, that you can't trust apostolic tradition, you have to
just go with the Bible. And in order to make that argument, they're arguing
against Saint Irenaeus quoting Scripture in favor of a tradition that
they've received that is not in the Bible, right, that Christ's ministry was
three years long.
as a great man once said irony could be so ironic sometimes I see I thought you
were gonna say that dog don't hunt but you know no no a great man once said nine
times out of ten with me is William Shatner in this case airplane to the
sequel but yeah so yeah so that is the most self-refuting argument
right on the face of the earth, right?
St. Irenaeus' quoting of St. John's Gospel is obviously wrong because I have received
this extra biblical tradition that Christ's ministry was exactly three years long.
And that proves that you prove Sola Scriptura.
Yeah.
Wow.
So there we are.
And people, people, and could, and could...
including intelligent people, including an intelligent person.
I might be debating next spring, make this argument all the time.
Hmm.
We're all going to be tuning in for that one.
That just and don't seem to realize how self-defeating that is.
Yeah.
Right.
So I just thought I would comment on that because I don't know.
I have a feel any, any time senior day comes up and we're going to be
talking more about him for the rest of this episode for two more halves
at least.
Is somebody in the comments somewhere somewhere he said Jesus 50 so
Let's just let's just dispense with that
Right. I think the best counter to that if you're a listener and someone throws that at you the future is just to look at them
I'd ask them. How do you know he's wrong?
Yeah, yeah
So I changed I'm needed. Yeah, how do you know? I mean he doesn't say 50, but how do you know Jesus?
wasn't in his forties when he died. Yep. Yep. So there you
get. All right. Well, you've you've wasted. No, you've spent
well another hour of your life on the Lord of Spirits podcast
this powered by generators, gas generators there, Northwestern
Indiana edition of the podcast. We're going to take a quick
break and we'll be right back. Father Andrew Steven
and father Stephen DeYoung will
We'll be back in a moment to take your calls on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Ancient Near Eastern texts such as the Baal Cycle portray the pagan god Baal as a rebel.
The hero of a revolution worshipped and glorified for his long string of victories.
In the Baal book, A Biography of the Devil,
Father Stephen the Young shows that the Hebrew scriptures consciously turned the Baal story on its head,
depicting him as a failed and defeated rebel who nonetheless tries to steal the glory that belongs to Almighty God.
From these scriptures, the figure of the devil emerged within Jewish and Christian tradition.
Father Stephen works through the Old and New Testament passages that refer to various Baal stories,
and he surveys Baal worship through followers' beliefs, religious practices, and liturgical life
to show that the f***
figures of Baal and the Devil, the Prince of Demons, are one in the same. You can find
the Baal book at store.ancientfaith.com. That's store.ancientfaith.com.
live AF radio. Hey, welcome back everybody. And thanks for that voice of Steve. I was
just texting with the voice of Steve earlier this morning, actually. How do you text with
a voice? Maybe he has voice to text set up. If anybody does, yeah, actually, you know,
Steve does great works, the great work these days. He is the the head of Focus Fellowship
of orthodox christians united to serve like doing actual good things for actual good
people and bad people too probably for a minute there I thought you were gonna say
he had he had become the lead singer for focus the Dutch Prague rock band who
made the classic hocus pocus wow I mean it's it's hard to imagine that band with
a Greek Cypriot lead singer but okay okay you would be very short compared to
to all the other Dutch people in the band.
That's true.
But he would keep his hair.
much longer. He definitely has the hair of his people as my wife once said to him in person.
Poor Steve, probably getting a bunch of text messages right now. Like,
do you know what they just said about you in Laura's beard?
Now he is a disembodied voice with hair.
That's right. That's right. He has very good hair. Very good hair.
Anyway, so we're talking about St. Irenaeus of Lyon and, you know, from whom we have
plagiarized so many things on this podcast for the last six years. And so now we're
We're gonna lay bare all of
the the we're talking about some of them things the bold theft yes exactly exactly so yeah we're
talking about on the apostolic preaching or the demonstration of the apostolic no no calls yet
well um or do they have to wind up a thing to answer the phone we have we have some calls that
are not entirely about our topic do you want to take an off topic call why not okay all right
well then we have a little thing like a topic between friends indeed indeed well we have we
We have Ilya.
calling from Chicago. So, Ilya, from Chicago, welcome to Laura Spirit's podcast.
Thank you so much. Father's bless.
God bless you. Did you get bad weather up there in Chicago?
It was absolutely horrible. We lost power everywhere.
Do you have power back yet?
Yeah, it got back. Then we got another tornado, and now there was power, no power for two days,
and now we got it back yesterday.
Well, you did sign up for li-
in the windy city. So I feel like tornadoes are unfortunately. Yeah. Yeah. Well, thanks
for calling in even in the midst of an apocalypse of sorts. I assume this is not professional
wrestler Ilya Draganov. That's not me. No, unfortunately, you're not talking to that
guy. Dude, you could have just said yes. And yeah, you guys would have never known
actually so yeah yeah just say the Russian accent is accent you do on TV is
fake, you know, it's like, yeah, exactly. Yeah. So, so what's up, Elia? I have a question
for you guys. Um, I'm a cradle Macedonian orthodox. Um, they kind of fell out with the
faith, um, for a majority of my life because nobody in my family was particularly educated
about, um, orthodoxy and never went to church only on Easter and Christmas. I'm sure
guys are aware of that kind of moving towards that kind of practice.
and CEO, CEO Christians we call them Christmas Easter only.
Yep, literally.
And so that's kind of where I grew up
and then I moved to the US about six years ago
with my parents.
And kind of after COVID,
I started kind of looking for something deeper.
I heard your talk, Father Andrew about this,
which is kind of crazy, which it related to me.
And I went through completely different worldviews.
I checked out Islam, unfortunately,
and Roman Catholicism and Protestantism.
I know.
found rest in any of them. But when I went to the orthodox church, I went there to debate
my local parish priest. And eventually that ended up shooting me in the foot because I
became active every single day and I'm an iconographer and an altar server. So how
is that shooting yourself in the foot? I mean, that's, you know, welcome home, buddy.
Yeah, that's the most beautiful bullet I could have ever received. But I guess
The point I'm trying to make is that I hold catechism classes for the
youth and I always I always get a question about Holy Communion that I I've been struggling
with myself and I've never found the answer to and that is when I was first coming back
into the faith when I was still learning I didn't know anything nobody around me was
kind of educated and unfortunately please fathers pray for me and may God forgive
me for this I would not hold the midnight fast I would eat in the morning sometimes
I would even show up to church hungover still feeling a little bit under the influence
Steven, like.
sometimes even chewing gum and I would spit the gum out
right before receiving communion, I would receive it
and then put another piece of gum back in my mouth.
And looking at it, looking at it back now,
like I'm thankful that God spared me and spared my life
because when I read St. Paul's Epistles,
as you guys know, people would die if they did that.
So I don't know how to feel about that.
I don't know what your guys' thoughts are about that.
And I don't know where that line is.
Is that me?
Midnight Fast kind of there to kind of set some sort of fear into people so that they
do receive communion more faithfully or reverently.
I don't know.
What do you guys think about this?
Yeah.
Well, I mean, number one, what you do to prepare for Holy Communion is a conversation that
if you've not had it with your father confessor, then you need to have that conversation.
And then whatever he says to do, do that.
But speaking generally, right?
So don't take this as...
Wait, what if he tells you to like rob a bank or kill somebody? I think that's unlikely. Now we off. Okay. Okay. Well, there we are
It would mean he's a supreme jokes director. Anyway, yeah, but you know speaking generally, right?
The the the Eucharistic fast is
Yeah, it's it's about preparing you in a state of reverence. There's a lot of things one could say about it
One is, you know, it emphasizes our, that our deepest hunger is for Christ. And so he's the first,
the first food that we receive on the days that we're going to receive Holy Communion.
And also fasting is traditionally a form of purification, right? So
fasting helps us to be repentant and to clean out sin. It's been observed that fasting is often
and great for dealing with all kinds.
of inordinate desires, just put it that way, and puts us into a state of greater peace if done
well under the guidance of our Father Confessors. So obviously, ignoring the fast, chewing gum
immediately before and after receiving the Holy Eucharist, this is not how we do things,
Ilya, and I'm sure your father confessor would probably say the same thing right after
telling you to go rob a bank, apparently. Yeah, it's about reverence, right? If you were
going to meet somebody really important, would you go in with a big chew of gum? I hope not,
right? That's rude. And all the more so when it is the one who made you, the one who is
the king of kings and lord of lords right so it's not only about fast
and what you put in your mouth. It's also about how you dress, the attitude that you have,
you know, get a good night's sleep, like all of these things like to really prepare for this
meeting with our God, which is what the Divine Liturgy is. And even if for some reason you can't
commune, like there's other reasons sometimes that you can't commune, if you can make it to church,
It's still good to do those things, if possible, just to remember in whose presence.
you are, you know, and to practice a little bit of humility. So, yeah, I mean, receiving
Holy Communion worthily is about that posture of repentance, of chastity, all of those things
together, right? We come humbly before God. So, yeah, I don't know, Father, anything
more you'd like to add or subtract or multiply or divide.
that none of those rules are there to be legalistic, right? Like, there are people who are diabetic,
they're, you know, women get pregnant, people have to take medications. For various reasons,
they're allowed to eat a little bit, not like steak and eggs, but eat a little bit,
you know, in the morning and still receive, right? And so it's about the larger issues
that Father Andrew was just talking about.
right, of reverence and preparedness and this kind of thing. And the specific rules are
general for most people, because for most people, they're things that help them do that. Yeah.
So yeah, that's yeah. Yeah, exactly. So all right, well, I hope that helps, Ilya. Thank
you very much for calling. Yeah, thank you so much, father seriously. Yeah, it does
clear things up. I mean, that was a few years ago.
I did that now looking back. I'm like, I can't believe I did that. But it was just more of a
question of was that more of God's grace allowing me to do that without kind of killing me because
I didn't know. You know, that was kind of like my question. I mean, every moment we're above ground
and rather below it is grace from God. So thank God. Amen. Thank God for all of that. And stay
safe. They're in in Chi Town and hope everything gets back to normal pretty soon. God willing.
Thank you sir.
God bless you guys here. Yeah. Yeah. All right. We're gonna go ahead. I don't know if that's a true
If that's a true statement, what's that?
Then every every moment we're alive in this world is sincerely is grace
Yeah, I think sometimes their life being brought to an end can be a grace. Well, of course
It's all grace father Stephen
Well now you sound like Calvinist everything action now
I didn't say that, but we're going to clip that one out.
We're going to clip that one out and that'll be like Father Andrews, even David Calvinist
secret. That's right. He venerates Saint Cyril Lucaris because he lived in Lithuania.
True story. We're going to take another call. So we've got Luke calling from Colorado. Luke,
welcome to Laura Spears podcast. Brothers, what? God bless you. What's on your mind, Luke?
So, I was reading the story of a
Elijah on his sheaths with my kids. And I came across the name of Jezebel's father, which
is S. Baal. And I have been taught by this show that that's an important thing to go look
up what that means, so I did. And it said that it means something like, Baal is with
me. And I had a confused moment because I knew in Hebrew that there's another thing
the King and God is with me, which is Emmanuel.
And I'm wondering if Father Stevens might be able to speak to a little bit as to what
the difference is between those two roots or meanings.
I may be teased out that S might mean something like a guardian daemon or genius or something.
And Emanuel L might mean something more like what we mean when we say crisis among us
or in our midst.
And the other piece of information here was...
that there doesn't appear to be any Yahweh, the euphoric or F, like there is. So anyways,
just a question.
Alright, well that's all you, Abuna. I don't know anything about the Phoenician dynastic
politics.
Uh, I mean, I am. Yeah. So Baal is really it's a Baal, uh,
in Phoenician, uh,
And interestingly, he started out his life as a priest, and a priest of a starte, not
Baal, and then murdered the king of Sainte and took over in a coup, and that's one of
the reasons why he married off.
Jezebel to Omri's air Ahab in Israel was he is trying to after said coup sort of secure
his position by making strategic alliances with his neighbors.
Yeah, and so it does mean something like either bail is with him or he is with bail, right?
the with the theophoric part of the difference between that and like so a manual is
God is with us, right? So there's a first person plural ending in the Emanue part. M or M is with in Hebrew.
And so you're talking about the difference between M and it and that's a it with with a it's an it h
Kind of sound which is the
a dialectical difference between Hebrew and Phoenician. So they're similar structures,
but the, it's a difference between third person singular in the case of etbal and first
person plural with Emanuel. That's why they look so different. And
Um, it was probably, um, like I would, I wouldn't go so far as to say it was that they believe
that he was full on demonically possessed. It was more like the idea of, uh, the way we look at
guardian angels, but the way they looked at spirits and gods, right? That that at his birth,
he was sort of dedicated to Baal.
And the quid pro quo of that was that Baal would then sort of service his patron and sort of help and assist him through his life.
And so he probably would have given credit for his successful coup to Bale.
And that is after all kind of an imitation of what Bale did, the whole coup thing.
Thank you.
So, I think that's the connection of what's going on there.
Yeah. Does that make sense, Luke? I mean, it's all past me, but...
Yes, yes. I should have said you're Hebrew right on the Latin in school, apparently.
Yes.
This is a mathematical change. Do you think it's relevant or meaningful at all that there...
Or am I just wrong about this?
that there are no kings of Israel or Hebrew names
that have that.
like the singular form of the Yahweh sephoric? Like is that something, for example, that would be
inappropriate to, you know, kind of claim that over Yahweh, for example? I mean, Elijah. Elijah's
name, yeah, is my God is Yahweh. Yeah, Eliyahu, yeah. Okay. So that's first verse in singular.
He's not a king but he's definitely a priest.
significant person. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Okay. Well, yeah. And
Elisha is, is God is my salvation. Joshua is Yahweh is Yahweh
saves. There's not a first person in there. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
So alright, well, thanks very much for calling Luke. So we're
talking about St. Irenaeus. And now we're going to go ahead
and get into the actual contents of on the Apostolic
preaching so uh... yes now for something completely
different. Not related to Phoenician dynastics. I have to say this just because I want to see
what you say, because I don't know if you read the chat. But there's, there's multiple
people in the chat that want me to ask this question. Are you guys, are you ready chat?
Are you ready? This is the question they're asking. Are aliens demons? Yes. There you
go. All right, moving on. Okay. Okay, assuming he's space aliens.
Yeah, not, not illegal aliens. No human being is illegal, Father Stephen. But they might be doing
something illegal. I reckon I could be outlawed any day now. How do you know you haven't already
been in absentia? Yes, I probably have. At least in Terre Haute, after all those unpaid Columbia
your house. Oh, yeah, bills. Yeah. Stonehenge. Yeah, I'm an outlaw.
like Jesse James, but only in Terre Haute, Indiana.
So yeah, so the rest of this episode,
we're just gonna be kind of talking our way through
on the Apostolic Preaching by St. Irenaeus.
And he begins at the beginning,
which is a very good place to start.
And that is with the creation
Thank you very much for watching!
the world. But interestingly, when he talks about the creation of the world, so he's literally
starting in Genesis, because he's going to go through Genesis. He's going to like walk
through Genesis interpreting it and then go into the rest of the Torah in this. So this
this half we're going to be talking about sort of part one of on the Apostolic preaching
and then we're going to talk about part two.
the third half. Yeah. But so in part one, he starts with with right at the beginning of Genesis, but
what he emphasizes there, this sort of shows you what we're talking about
in terms of a way of reading is he is very quick to want to point out the key thing for him at
the very beginning of the book of Genesis, those first few verses is the Holy Trinity.
that God, and here by God he means the Father, God the Father, creates everything through
his Word, which he identifies as being Christ, right, the Son, and his wisdom, which he identifies
as being the Holy Spirit, right, and you see the Holy Spirit hovering over the waters
at the beginning of Genesis, you see him create by speaking, right, so he's creating
through his word. And so
He's interpreting that
You know funnily enough he doesn't try and figure out the date
How long ago it was he's not concerned that he's concerned with here right away first verses of the Bible we see the holy trinity
Yeah, right, so this is a principle that's gonna go all the way through
His reading of scripture. He is going to be reading scripture in a trinitarian way
Okay
Yeah, but we get to the second half you will definitely see this
Because he's gonna do a lot of Christ in the Old Testament stuff
That's where we stole that from
But right so he's reading it in a trinitarian way that's part of the rule of faith
It's part of the tradition is the the holy trinity, right?
And he even uses he doesn't use the word homo usios, but he uses usia in talking about the trinity
the relationship between the father and the son, he uses the word epistasis in Greek, right?
Like, so again, sorry, Charlie, all the, the doctor tree developed over time and blah, blah,
blah, blah, blah, blah, blah, blah, right? No, hardly. Yes. No. Yeah. Right. And so
he moves from talking about sort of the, the prologue of the creation in Genesis.
to the creation of the angelic beings by talking about the seven heavens and the seven spirits and
The seven works of the Holy Spirit and directly connecting sort of the creation of the angelic host
To the Holy Spirit as wisdom
So here again there is not
Some creation and fall of angelic beings
before the creation of the world. This is in the context of the creation of the world.
God creates the creation both visible and invisible, as the creed says here in St. Irenaeus.
And the cosmology that he lays out of these multiple heavens and the divine beings associated with each of the heavens,
none of that should be remotely unfamiliar to long-term listeners of this podcast.
Yes, yes, yes.
Yes. This is, again, this is basic stuff, but again, it's a way of reading, right?
And then when he talks about the creation of humanity in paradise, one of the things
he wants to emphasize really is that man is created as the ruler of the rest of creation.
Yeah.
yeah now there's a subtle thing here right because we've all heard that we've talked
out of the show, his naming of the animals, being a reflection of that, that's all true.
But he's just finished talking about the creation of the angelic beings.
And so his emphasis on that here, I mean, we're talking about like a medium-sized paragraph
and then the following medium-sized paragraph, right?
It's pretty clearly including the angelic beings.
in that category. So he has this understanding that we've pointed to a few times on the episode
that St. Andrew of Crete points out in his commentary on Revelation about the devil
falling through envy of humanity, right? You mean St. Andrew of Caesarea or Andrew of Crete?
St. Andrew of Caesarea, yeah. Caesarea, okay. Yeah, his comment on Revelation. Although the
devil falling through envy is in a lot of the church fathers. Is it a lot? That's what St.
Andrew says yeah yeah yeah it would not surprise me if it's all
also in St. Andrew of Crete, but it was St. Andrew of Caesarea that I mentioned.
Right, so he has this idea, right, that's there in terms of the motivation, right?
He then makes a very deliberate point of the fact that Adam and Eve in the Garden, in Paradise,
are innocent.
in childlike. Yeah, that they they need to grow up still. Yeah,
they're sinless, but not mature. Yes, they're innocent and
childlike. And where is he getting that? That's how what
he understands it to mean about them being naked and not
ashamed. Hmm, which, you know, as the father of four children,
I can tell you that there's a certain very young age. Yes,
you've got a one year old and a two year old, they can take
bath together and no, there's nothing there.
absolutely naked and unashamed. Like, stop, put your
clothes back on. Yeah, right. And so he he understands that to
mean this innocence, right? This childlike innocence, right,
which is their state before, right, before the tree.
And actually, I have it right in front of me. I just want to
read this for people just so you don't have to just believe
our summaries, right? This is what he
says, and this is also for those of you who are asking in the
chat, like, is this a really hard book to read? It's actually
not that hard. I was saying in the chat, it's not as easy as
like scenic nations of Antioch, it was pretty easy to read. But
it's not that hard. So this is what he says in that section,
he says, and this is on page 48, if you have the paperback
version. And Adam and Eve, for this is the name of the
woman, were naked and were not ashamed. Since there was in
them an innocent and childlike mind, and they thought or
understood nothing.
whatsoever of those things which are wickedly born in the soul through lust and shameful
desires, because at that time they preserved their nature intact, since that which was
breathed into the handiwork, that, you know, they are God's handiwork, was the breath
of life and while the breath remains in its order and strength that is without comprehension
or understanding of what is evil, and thus they were not ashamed, kissing and embracing
each other in holiness as children.
Like that's the word he uses, like that they're childlike, innocent, like children.
Yes, yeah, and again, that is theologically important because that's different than saying that they were perfect
Yeah, yeah
Because perfect sinless and perfect are not the same thing
right
You know perfect seems fully fully grown fully matured, right?
Yes mature complete in virtue, etc. Right
When they then eat of the tree of the knowledge of good and evil,
St. Eurus says that by this man has made a sinner.
Yeah.
And they ruined himself.
I'm seeing this right now.
Ahri so, ah, sorry, ahri oh oh.
He ruined himself.
Yeah.
Interesting.
But, yeah.
There's nothing about guilt here.
There's nothing about being guilty.
I will do
punishment. It's he's now made a sinner. And he's he's ruined.
He's broken, you know, distorted. Yeah, his nature is now
distorted, broken, inclined towards sin, right? The devil
here by St. Ernest is attributed as having sort of create
brought evil into existence in so far as it exists, right? The
idea that he's the original angel becoming by falsehood,
the head and originator of sin.
was himself struck, having offended God and caused the man to be cast out of the paradise.
So yeah, the origin of sin is said by Saint Irenaeus here to be this angel, so a fallen angel,
right? This fallen angel. Who is the devil, who is Satan, right? He identifies all these with the
the with the serpent. Right. Um, but he is, he is in the origin of that. So then he goes
through the rest of the Torah. Very relatively quickly, but he talks about the exodus a little
bit. He's going to get into that more later. He talks about the wilderness wanderings
and the sin of the people in the wilderness as that sort of being the, oh, before we
get there. Sorry. Yeah, something, something minorly important.
Yeah. At least to listeners of this show, something moderately important. He talks about
Cain and Abel of course, right? But then he talks about, hey, what happened with the flood?
And who are those Nephilim and those giants? Yeah. And he simply states as the apostolic
way of reading those verses that
Uh
Angelic beings had relations with women
Yeah
Yeah, and note note
taught them sorcery and
divination and
Cos I do adorn themselves to seduce them
Let me read that for everybody actually you got y'all gonna love this again. This is from the we swear. We're not making this up files
Yes, this is on page 50 in the paper
back. And wickedness spreading out for a long time seized the entire race of men until there
was very little seed of righteousness in them. For unlawful unions occurred on earth as angels
united themselves with daughters of men who bore them sons who because of their exaggerated
height were called giants. The angels then gave their wives as gifts wicked teachings
for they taught them the powers of roots and herbs of dying and cosmetics. And the
And the discovery of precious material love potions.
Hatreds, loves, infatuations, seductions, bonds of witchcraft, and all kinds of divination
and idolatry hateful to God.
There it is.
St. Irenaeus of Leon, everybody.
Yes, yeah.
But notice the co-location here in St. Irenaeus of these relations with the idea of sorcery,
right?
Yeah.
pharmacaya, right? That these things are brought together here. And so this is again
the view we've put forward here that reconciles the fathers,
right, that what is actually being described in terms of these relations by Saint Irenaeus
is participation in these pagan.
sexual rituals, right? Not angels literally having sexual relations with humans and producing
hybrid offspring, right? But describing these rituals. And it was recently brought to my
attention that a martyred priest, Father Daniel Cicero, Cicero, if, yeah, uh, in
published
First writings took the exact same view in terms of reconciling the fathers on this for
the same reason to reconcile the fathers on this.
He says that the early fathers who uniformly teach this were referring to pagan sexual
rituals.
Yeah.
That that's what they were talking about.
Not the little four.
He takes the exact same view and I didn't this is a case where I didn't steal this
from him.
I like I said, we've been saying this show for years. I found out like a few weeks ago. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah, it was kind of
He took the same view so he in Russia
right
Not that many years ago and me here in the United States with no knowledge arrived at the same conclusion
Still be wrong, but that's right
But it that means I guess it's not unprecedented, right?
That that's what's going on here, and let me put it in a dendym
For those of you who are unpersuaded that's cool
You don't have to you know be persuaded by everything I say because some of it probably is not correct
But you know the big
People's understanding of the alternative view people's understanding of the view of the that the later fathers adopt
Regardless
was sometimes called the Sethite Hypothesis or the idea that this is about the descendants
of Seth intermarrying with the daughters of Cain. Most of the folks today, including
Orthodox folks who disagree with us about this are not taking the view
of that that the church fathers had. They are taking a version of the Sathite hypothesis
that comes from modern scholarship, specifically modern non-Christian scholarship. The reason
they hold that view is that they believe that that part of Genesis was written after the exile.
Huh.
Because what-
was the big problem, if you've read the book of Ezra, after the exile. Jewish people intermarrying
with non-Jewish women.
Yeah. So they're reading that as being about prohibiting...
So they're reading that, yes. As them putting that, the priests in the P layer, that's
the priests, including Ezra himself, after the exile, adding that in.
condemn intermarriage to show intermarriage as being this this great sin and people happily adopt
this very modern very materialist reading. So what was the actual view that the church
fathers adopt? So we've argued that the reason they adopt this view is that because they didn't
have pagans around anymore in the 5th century starting in the 5th century they didn't understand
the ritual context.
of what St. Irenaeus was talking about, and so they, I was going to say you still get like it's
interesting, like St. Ephraim the Syrian in the Cave of Treasures, right, which is a really interesting
text, which includes like, you know, all kinds of what did Adam do after Genesis chapter four,
right? Genesis chapter three. In the Cave of Treasures, the way that St. Ephraim the Syrian
describes this is he takes the so-
Seth I'd view, right? He says it's the sons of Seth intermarrying with the daughters of
Cain. But then he says that the daughters of Cain are possessed by demons. Yeah. So, like,
which is exactly what we said back on episode seven of this podcast back in 2020.
He's in the fourth century, not the fifth century.
Fourth century. Yeah, but still, yeah, well, exactly. But I'm, you know, like he's pointing
at that and essentially saying like, like, he just gets there in a different way. Like,
It's the same thing the people who reject
it are in the fifth century. And they reject it. The it that they're rejecting is the idea
that there was literal sexual relations between an angelic being and a human and it produced
a hybrid offspring. Right. They always say that they're rejecting. They always say,
look, angels can't have have babies. That's explicitly explicitly. That's what they're
they're rejecting. And so we're just saying that's not what the earlier fathers were teaching.
Yeah, right. And we're harmonizing those. But the view that they took, so the view that
a Saint Augustine or a Saint John cash in took, right, was not this sort of materialist thing
of Oh, this is just about intermarriage being bad. No, right. Their view was that the descendants
of Seth, the reason they had these super long lifespans is because
They still had kind of holdover theosis.
Yeah, yeah, like the idea of like living, like they're living on the mountain of paradise, but they're not at the top anymore because they go up there anymore.
Right. Like the glory that that Adam was clothed in in paradise sort of faded slowly, not just from him, but from his line.
Yeah.
That's why he lives like 950 years and then going
down. So they believe that these people in the line of Seth were like super charged with
divine power. This is not a materialist view. No. Okay. And that's why they're called sons
of God. Yeah. According to this view, because they're like, and then they're going and sleeping
with the heathen. Yeah, the people down at the bottom of the mountain, who are all
all kinds of
evil and not worshiping God, opposed to God, right? These demonized people, okay? So the
view that St. John Chrysostom, St. John Cashion, St. Augustine actually held is way closer
to our view, right? Actually, then it is to that kind of materialist view that a lot
of our would be.
ops, uh, have chosen to adopt, uh, out there in internet land.
Got some, but yeah, and they're actually like, we're the ones who aren't
patristic, but anyway, I have a slight digression that I just wanted to
bring up because I just thought this was so cool.
Cause I was thinking about cave of treasures.
Uh, there's a fun, fun bit about that where basically, so
Seth and his family are there up, if they're on the side of the
mountain and part of the
their job is to actually take care of the relics of Adam, which are placed into this
cave of treasures. And you know, there's worship going on in this cave. So there's literally
like worship over relics going. I mean, this is wild stuff, right? That gets anyways.
But here's the bit I want to just point out because we were mentioning the flood
and also bring us back to the flood in the cave of treasures. When the flood comes,
it lifts the body of Adam up out of the cave of treasures and it gets washed away
And the skull?
gets washed all the way to Jerusalem and becomes the place of the skull, like Golgotha.
And that, of course, that is the skull of Adam. And that's the idea that when Jesus is crucified
on the cross, that his blood drips down on the skull of Adam. Anyway, yeah, all that cool,
cool stuff. That's not an Irenaeus. It's not an Irenaeus. But this is part of the lore of
know, the early church, right? You know, say,
My firm, as you said, is what fourth century is so basically, um, uh, in the same time period
as, you know, first couple ecumenical councils.
Pretty awesome.
All right, rolling on indeed, um, indeed.
So, uh, yeah.
So there, there we go.
Now we will get another round of, uh, all you talk about isn't nephilim.
Um
That's probably the longest bit. We've done on Giants since episode seven back in 2020. Yeah. Yeah, I think yeah
People I hope you're but it's it's their insane your days, right? So yes. Yes. I was just reading it. Just read that
So yeah, and he goes he goes through the the rest of the Torah to he even mentioned studer on me
You know how Moses gives them a second law
as it were on the the planes of Moab, right? And then he kind of jumps this part. Now he's
going to come back and do some more Old Testament stuff, but he goes in part two. But here in part
one, he sort of finishes with the Torah and then jumps to the incarnation. Yeah. And in order to
to talk about.
First Christ is the second Adam
Right that the incarnation is about him taking flesh like the flesh
That Adam was given
Right and this parallel and built right into it. He's very clear about it in the middle of the second century
The Theo toko says the second Eve
Yeah, yeah
And her virginity parallel to Eve's virginity
And not only does he present the Theotokos as the second Eve, meaning here's your basic
building block of Mariology, but you'd expect this because I'm not going to do it again now,
but I know on the show before I've talked about in St. John's Gospel and the Passion
account the way St. John in his gospel presents the Theotokos in relationship to Eve, right?
Intertextually right and who is saying you're an ass drawing on primarily?
traditions received from st. John
But he also presents the Theotokos as an advocate
For the human race well well well checkmate Protestants. Yes, how the turntables have turned
So actually I have to I
have to read this awesome passage, right? This is great. This is great. So this is on page 61.
Again, proving we're not making this stuff up. I love this. And just as through a disobedient
virgin, man was struck and falling died. So he means Eve, right? So also by means of a version
who obeyed the word of God, man being revivified received life. For the Lord came to seek back
the lost sheep and it was men who was lost.
therefore he did not become any other formation, but being born from her who was of the race
of Adam, he maintained the likeness of the formation. For it was necessary for Adam to
be recapitulated in Christ, that mortality might be swallowed up in immortality, and
Eve in Mary, that a virgin, and here's the way you said, become an advocate for
a virgin, might undo and destroy the virginal disobedience by virginal obedience. In
In other words, that the Virgin Mary is an advocate for the
her foremother and through her you get the destruction of disobedience. I mean
it's so cool like this is like this is just simply orthodox
myriology right here. Yeah. In the second century. St. Irenaeus. Yes. There's
the core of what a lot of you folks out there in Listenerland were told was
invented in the Middle Ages by an evil pope. Yeah. Yeah. This is long before. In the
second century, two generations.
after Saint John. Constantine wasn't even born yet, so you
can't play the blame. Constantine card. I'm sorry, you guys,
this is during a period of vicious persecution of the
church. Yep, yep. Anyway, fun. And that so after this, he's
going to he's going to talk about the cross and connect the
cross as a tree to the tree of the knowledge of good and
evil.
inversion. And the parallel from what you just read is key to this between disobedience
and obedience. Yeah. Um, that, uh, so, uh, the tree of knowledge of good and evil and
Adam's disobedience at that tree brought the knowledge of evil, right? Into the world
as we've talked about before the show, they knew God, so they knew good, right?
that this brought the dollar to be.
evil, right? Evil, as he has just talked about, grew, right? And the knowledge of good was
lost. Christ's obedience at the tree of the cross, then, St. Irenaeus points out in this
inversion, Christ's obedience at the tree of the cross, then brings the knowledge of
of good back, the knowledge of God back, right?
And so,
That knowledge of good then is the path of
Obedience
Right
The obedience of people people needing to be obedient to the commandments. What?
It's almost like if you love me you'll keep my commandments
Is a thing over and over again the pencil?
That's at the core of what St. Irenaeus says is going on at the crop
we'll come back to that, because he comes back to that in part two. Now he's been
arguing for, and you heard in the quote that Father Andrew just read, this
recapitulation, this idea that Christ by passing through these things
sanctifies them, transforms them, and this of course then is the basis of
of theoses of our transformation, right?
And so,
coming off of this understanding of the cross, he goes to theosis in Christ, being the fulfillment
of the promise made to Abraham about becoming like the stars of heaven, right? He just says
that straight out. Yeah, as lights in the world, he says, yes, make his seed as the
stars of heaven. Yep. Yep. This is all on page 63.
Yes. Yes. And he's also though he's going to go into this more in part two. He's also
Christ is also the fulfillment of the promise to David of the Messiah from his seed. And
And then he wants to, as we come toward the end of part one, the materiality.
the material reality, right? Because think about this and against heresies he's primarily
opposing narcissism. So materiality here is important. Material reality of the birth and
death and resurrection of Christ. Yeah, Christ was truly born in the flesh because if he wasn't
truly born he couldn't truly die and if he can't truly die he can't be risen from the dead
and therefore death isn't defeated and we're all hosed. Yeah, like he again like this is very
quote-unquote high Christology, right? So
like, I'll just read one section here. He said, Thus in this way, he gloriously accomplished
our salvation, fulfilled the promise made to the patriarchs and dissolved the old disobedience.
Listen to this, the Son of God become the Son of David and the Son of Abraham. For in accomplishing
and recapitulating these things in himself in order to obtain life for us, the Word
of God became flesh by the economy of the Virgin in order to undo death and vivify
man for we were in the prison of sin.
we who have become sinners and fallen under the power of death."
So he's very clear here that this is God and man, like this is not invented by the Council of Nicea.
Or Halsey, or yeah. Yeah, like it's just not, just not. Again, like so I tell people like,
look, if the only theology you have is this text, you're doing okay. Yeah, you're doing okay.
Well, and this, his whole argument out the material reality is basically the same.
argument St. Paul makes in 1 Corinthians 15. He never alludes to and he doesn't use the same
language as St. Paul, but it's the same argument. Yeah. Yeah. And Ignatius, I mean like, you know,
welcome to 2nd century Christianity everybody. It happens to be the same as what's in the
Bible. The same was in the 3rd and 4th century Christianity. I mean, it's just,
Yeah, it's just, you know, it turns out this is why I told me this is why I told
people. I have a lot of reasons for having become orthodox and even more for staying orthodox.
But this is why I tell people that when I really started actually reading particularly the second
century church fathers, in other words, the next century after the New Testament, I was
like, I just, I just can't stay Protestant. And like everything I'm seeing here is what
orthodoxy teaches now. Like anyone who's been through catechism, there's nothing
that we're reading here from Irenaeus that should be kind of a surprise, maybe the
giant stuff.
maybe they didn't cover that in Catechism. But the rest of this is pretty straightforwardly
just, you know, Orthodoxy 101, I think, as they say, yeah. Yeah. And so he kind of ends with
the first section with talking about how now all of the nations have been called in Christ to
abandon idolatry and sexual immorality, those being again, just like in Scripture, those
That was big.
paradigmatic big sins, right? And to follow Christ. And by follow Christ, he means live
the way Christ lived, be obedient the way Christ was obedient, because that will cause
you to be saved from death.
Yeah, he doesn't say just agree with this or say this prayer.
Yeah.
So, all right. Well, that's the end of part one of On the Apostolic Preaching by
St. Irenaeus of Lyon.
We're going to take our second final break for this episode of the Lord Spirit's podcast.
We'll be right back.
Father Andrew Stephen Daymick and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment to take
your calls on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346, that's 855-AF-Radio.
Can its creatures sense holiness?
Can a single walk across a land bridge change everything?
Journey to the windswept shores of Holy Island in the Island and St. Aden, a beautifully
written and illustrated chapter book that brings to life the first meeting between St.
Aden, known as the Apostle of Northumbria and the Island of Lindisfarne, discover
how an island and its creatures are transformed by the presence of a saint.
The Island and St. Aidan, now available at store.angelfaith.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Steven Damick and Father Steven
DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF-RADIO.
Hey, welcome back, everybody.
On this episode of the Lord of Spirits podcast, we're talking about the blatant plagiarism
that we've been...
You're taking for years now from St. Irenaeus of Lyon on the Apostolic preaching, one of
the greatest of the Second Century Church Fathers, really, everyone should have this
in their library.
And read it.
Don't just put it on your shelf.
Actually, read it.
And, yes, someone in the chat was just saying, my books, my books, you can just buy and
put on your shelf because I get the royalties when you buy them.
You don't have to actually read them, but you should read St. Irenaeus.
Yes.
Absolutely.
you know, it, like I said, it's a little bit
more difficult than, you know, St. Ignatius of Antioch, who's, you know, from 75, maybe
years earlier, not that much earlier, but still not that bad. I mean, I've been reading
some passages here. And, you know, if you're not used to reading this kind of thing, you
might have to kind of puzzle over a sentence here and there. But, you know, there's a
yeah, it's, it's great. It's great. Actually, I was just, I was just looking at the
first page of the second part and I was noticing that he
He's quoting Hebrew. Actually, he didn't know the same days. No Hebrew sort of okay. So yeah, well, we'll get into that here
The minute okay. All right. All right. I'm interested in this cuz I don't know
Interesting, but it's not totally kosher shall we say okay unintended nice. All right, okay
Part two first we have any calls. Yeah, let's see. Do we have any calls? I'm
You're not even paying attention to calls. I'm not I'm you know, I'm I'm not seeing anything
anything here, but Mike is typing something. What is it that he's going to be typing? He's
going to say, look, people are just intimidated. They don't want to call in a possible off-topic
caller. So let's just take it. Just take them. All right. So yeah, just flip that switch,
Mike. Who knows who this is? Welcome to Laura Spears podcast off-topic caller, possibly.
We need to interact with the community. Hey, this is Owen and I'm with my friend
Brandon and we're from Rochester Hills, Michigan.
And we've been listening to you guys podcast the past couple months and discerning worth the box to you
We're just thankful for you guys do and it's helped us learn a lot. So thank you. All right. Well, thanks for calling in your hosers
I
Have to call people from Michigan that because I have Michigan cousins
If you you know if you are like around
Not exactly Kalamazoo, but in that general area and you run into somebody named Daimik
That is almost certainly someone I'm related to and there's not a lot of them
Thank you very much for your time.
So almost certainly someone that I'm related to those and their date the other day mix
If you happen to be in or around Kalamazoo and you run into someone with the last name Heisinga
They are definitely related to me. There you go. There you go
There's there's if you might see like a pair of people walking a couple of guys walking around that look just like me and father Stephen
Anyway, what's what what is it Owen and Brandon all right?
We've got a Welsh, Welsh name and an Irish name. So Celtic fringe there. Okay. So, so what's on your minds, gentlemen?
But I remember in one of the pandemonium the question episodes
Father Steven and you were answering a question about Matthew seven where it's about the narrow gate
And the wide gate and the way of Evia leads to destruction. And I remember you guys were talking about how
This isn't necessarily like a binary view of how many people are safe
It's not like a count of numbers and that made sense and how the way that it's hard leads
to life is talking about the saints and that makes sense to me, but it's really hard for
me to get around the language of leading to destruction and that not necessarily being
a salvific thing if that makes sense.
Like when I'm reading it seems very hard to take myself out of the admittedly Protestant
paradigm of looking at it, but it starts for me to not see that as a way of salvation
in a way of destruction because the language seems very...
kind of centered around that that makes sense I'm it doesn't make sense to me but uh
family repars that father do you get picking up what he's laying down
not really like we weren't denying that we were I think the confusion is so we were saying
we weren't saying that there's not a way that leads to destruction right uh there
certainly is. And it is, in various ways, easy, right? But we were we rejected the idea that
there are people who, based on that statement, say, oh, only a tiny minority of the people
in the world will be saying. Yes, most people are damned. And so we were saying that numerical
thing is not what that statement is about. Yeah.
Right.
Just because there's two ways, and one is easy and the other is hard,
doesn't mean that every, you know, it's not like those memes,
you know, where you see everybody going to the easy thing,
you know, they're going to fall off a cliff or whatever.
So the purpose of saying that, that's not like just a brand new idea
that Christ revealed.
That's all through the Old Testament wisdom literature,
the two ways, right?
It's all over proverbs, right?
And it continues going in the DDK, right?
that's
the right there's the way of life and the way of death right the idea that there's these two ways
and so Christ was was pointing out he was using that two-way metaphor to talk about
the fact that if you're going to pursue life that way is difficult and requires effort
right unlike unlike the other that's his central point
He's not trying to give a ratio
of what ratio of humanity is saved or not.
Yeah.
The way it's sometimes quoted.
So you could, a parable is like an extended analogy.
And an analogy is a comparison in one respect only.
That's a quote from Thomas Aquinas.
But meaning like when Christ says that faith
is like a mustard seed, it doesn't mean that,
you know, okay, go look up mustard seeds
in encyclopedia, like.
Everything that's true of a mustard seed is true of faith, right? Like I mean, he was making a specific
comparison, right?
In one respect, he was saying these are comparable. That doesn't mean you could push the analogy or the metaphor
Yeah, how about that Owen? Do you feel satisfied now? Yeah, that
Yeah, that makes a lot of sense
Especially looking at it coming from like trying to limit what?
trying to build more upon that going past when you said that makes a lot of
sense. Good. All right. All right. Well, thank you very much for calling. You
guys sound like you're driving in the car. Is that right? You're driving in
Michigan? Yeah. Well, actually, we're from Rochester. We're in Canada right now.
Oh, you're with it with the the the greater hosers. Yes,
in Afghanistan. All right. Well,
Say hello to Canada for us
Home of you know the world's greatest Canadian and the world's second-grayest Canadian actually probably most of the world's greatest Canadians live in Canada
So all right
Thanks for calling
Let's see. I'm not seeing any other calls there on the board. So I guess people are just super into your names
They're just really super focused. So they're hanging on every word. That's me every syllable
Yep. Yep. Yep. All right. So what is
In part two of On the Episod Preaching, Father Stephen.
A bunch of stuff.
Stuff.
More stuff.
Yeah.
The, my, my, when we moved down here nine years ago to Lafayette, my wife was kind of ticked
at me when we got down here because I packed some of the boxes of course and therefore
I labeled them and so there were boxes that said things on them like stuff and
junk.
Yeah.
My, my, my, my version of that
is miscellaneous. Yeah, miss straight for but but I distinguished
between stuff and junk, right? Like, it's a value judgment. Yes,
like stuff is well, it's just a bunch of stuff, whereas junk is
just like, I just a bunch of junk, right? We should have
thrown this away, but somehow it got packed. You empty out a
desk drawer into a box. That's junk. Well, that was a
junk drawer. Right? Take all the things that are sitting
on the desk and put them in a box and that's stuff.
Yeah. See, right. So there's, there's a clear, um, yeah, but she, she somehow felt that wasn't
communicative enough. So, you know, what could I say? Um, alas. So yeah, so appropriately
enough, uh, since one of St. Irenaeus' main themes is this idea of recapitulation, uh,
the second part two, right?
The second half sort of.
It's not roughly half right of on the Apostolic preaching cycles back and kind of repeats from
a different perspective the first half.
So he goes back to the beginning of Genesis and walks through the same thing again to
the end but just from a different perspective, right?
And so he goes back to the beginning of Jesus, and as Father Andrew pointed out...
There is the first line
Yeah, in Hebrew of Genesis Bersheep brah Elohim Hashem I am the heart's a
Little I don't want to say crudely transliterated into Greek because of course it was
Transliterated into Greek and then transliterated from Greek into old Armenian before we get right the right
And then father John bear just you know
rendered the transliteration which because he starts out by saying most
who prophesied first says in Hebrew and then he gives it. Right, so he gives this Hebrew quote,
which is, like I said, roughly transliterated, but remember it's passed through a couple of languages.
So that accounts for a lot of the roughness. Now, you know, Father Andrew asked, did he know
Hebrew? He does something interesting here with the Hebrew. So I've commented before that,
You know, we're all you.
to hearing this text translated from the Hebrew as, in the beginning, God created the heavens
and the earth. If you've listened to the whole Council of God episode on Genesis 1.1, back
of the day. Then you heard me say that actually a closer translation
of the Hebrew, maybe a better translation of the Hebrew would be at the beginning of
His creation, God made the heavens and the earth.
So interestingly, in terms of grammatical structure, St. Irenaeus reads it that way.
with it.
difference. So when I translate that is at the beginning of his
creating, he made the heavens of the earth. I am that creation at
the beginning of his creation, the word creation there is the
word Barah in Hebrew. And St.
Thank you.
It's very common in the first and second centuries.
This even happens at one point in the New Testament to refer to Aramaic as the Hebrew
language, because it's sort of the language of the Hebrews, right?
It's the language they spoke at the time in the first century.
centuries. It's Aramaic, which is technically a different dialect than Hebrew. And if you
know even a little Aramaic, even the tiniest bit, you might know what Bar means in Aramaic.
son. Yeah. Right. So like Barabbas in the New Testament is actually bar Abbas.
being son of, right? Or we're told Barnabas, Bar Nabas means son of encouragement. Right?
So he reads that barra as bar. And so he translates the Hebrew. Hmm. You see what I'm saying,
Father Andrew? Yeah, you're probably looking at the text of your name. Yeah, yeah, he translates
Well, so the way the father John.
renders it is. It's kind of clunky, but I think that's what I think he's trying to render the
clunkiness. A son in the beginning, God established then heaven and earth.
Yes. So it's like at the beginning of his creation, he made the heavens of the earth,
but he changed our creation to sun. A son at the beginning, God created, then the heavens
the earth. So yeah, he's kind of, he's kind of reading it sideways as
Aramaic and thereby literally putting the sun in the beginning of sun. God
created the heavens of the earth, right? So he's, he's literally placing the sun
beginning with God. Yeah, to allude to as he has said here at
AS does in the following passage alluding to the prologue to
Saint John's Gospel. So like I said, that's not really kosher in
Hebrew like that's not really. But it shows it gives you the
idea again of how he's reading. Yeah. Yeah, I mean, what could
say he's reading Genesis 1 in terms of John 1.
Yeah, yeah, it may be over literalizing it a little right in that the language can't actually do that, but
Right like a Jewish person
Who was interacting with St. Irenaeus?
at the time would not have bought that argument
it was fluid in Hebrew, but
We get the point he's making
Interest well, we'll come back to that so
And he doesn't stop there
in terms of understanding Christ in the text of the Torah because he goes that to
The Oak of Mamre Abraham at the Oak of Mamre and that's Christ who comes and visits and eats with him
Yeah, he just says and again Moses says that the son of God drew near to speak with Abraham and God appeared to him by the
Oak of Mamre at midday etc etc
right and
Then he goes on to have Christ at Bethel
Yeah, with Jacob seen by Jacob
And then Christ is involved in the Exodus. Yep hanging out talking to Moses
Right
And defeating Amalek here's Giants again, right? Let's get excited
Right defeating the spiritual Amalek
For us by stretching out his arms on the cross, right
Um, and so he then, uh, sort of gives a little summary thing where he argues and he uses
a whole bunch of language.
It's going to be used by the later councils and Father John is a good job of pointing
this out.
Um, it is translation by giving the Greek terms, um, he says that father and son are
both God.
They're both Lord, right?
But the father is invisible and inaccessible.
And so the Son gives access to the Father, to God.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Yeah, again.
That's his argument.
Quote, quote, high Christology where he says, literally, the Father is Lord, and the Son
is Lord, and the Father is God, and the Son is God.
But wait, I saw a meme that said this was invented by Constantine in the 4th century.
He literally uses the terms Eusea and Epistah.
right exactly it's crazy so right but again and he's saying this in the
context of the Old Testament yeah yeah but again what is St. John saying is
prologue no one has seen God at any time but the unique God or the unique son
depending on your who is it the bosom of the father has made him known right
I don't.
So this is he's fleshing that out in terms of the Old Testament.
And then let me just quote what he says.
Since the Father of all is invisible and inaccessible to creatures,
it is necessary for those who are going to approach God to have access to the Father
through the Son. That's what he says. Just straight up.
Right. And notice, notice he's making this as an ontological statement.
Yeah. Meaning this isn't because of sin.
No, right
This is a across-the-board statement
Right
So then he moves to
Psalm 110
Yes, most quoted and you can see how he would move from that the flow of thought. He's just said the father and son are both Lord
Right
Well, the Lord said to my Lord, that's how someone 10 starts, right?
As we've commented before on the show, I know Psalm one 10
is the most quoted scripture in the New Testament.
Yeah. And it's basically the subject of the epistle to the Hebrews.
Yes.
I've argued that Hebrews is basically a homily delivered by St.
Paul on Psalm one 10.
So.
And he walks through that, right, and connects other passages.
So Christ in the Incarnation is both the Divine King and the Human King descended from David.
And so he works through, right, all of the Messianic prophecies regarding David's seed
then from the Old Testament.
So he talks about the king coming from Judah in Genesis.
Yep. Yep. He talks about the star coming from Judah in numbers, which is Balaam, right?
He attributes all this to Moses because he sees Moses as the author of the Torah. He talks about the sprout from Jesse's sit down
Right or the shoot depending on your translation from Jesse stem, right?
He talks about the restoration of David's fallen tabernacle, which also gets quoted in the book of Acts
and applied to to Christ
But again, with all of these things, all of these things we're referencing get quoted in
different parts of the New Testament and applied to Christ.
But St. Irenaeus doesn't quote that New Testament application.
He quotes the Old Testament and does what the New Testament is doing.
Yeah, he's, if we may put it this way, a successor to the apostles.
Right.
The rule of faith for him is reading the Old Testament scriptures the way the apostles
did.
where do you see that in the New Testament? So the New Testament is not just this set
of doctrinal propositions and dogmas that you are sent to. The New Testament is an example
you follow. Yeah, right. That's a really important point. Yeah. And then he culminates, right?
He's going through all these Old Testament prophecies.
of the Messianic King, he culminates in Christ's triumphal entry into Jerusalem, right? The event.
But he spends this big chunk of time there arguing, and before Saul Boatheon is the Torah, right? He's
arguing here, the central to this argument is that Jesus is the Jewish Messiah. And so this is
It's another important thing we have to remember and it isn't taught this way.
There is this weird presupposition out there.
I mean I know where it comes from because we've a bunch on this show we've talked about
and this is debunking this is the core of what religion of the apostles is about.
This idea that like Christianity is a new religion that starts from scratch and okay
now we're done with Judaism thing and we're gonna write.
sophisticated
than that, you have, okay, yes, Christianity starts out within Judaism, but by the middle
of the second century, they're completely separate. Christians have all been thrown out
of synagogues and everything is, and everything is separate. And that's not the case either.
No, I mean, Irenaeus, this is just not his approach at all. He just simply treats
the Old Testament as a Christian book and as the Christian religion that he's part
Yes, and Judaism is still in view.
making an argument that Christianity, that Jesus is the Messiah and so Christianity is the fulfillment
is the continuation of the religion of the Old Testament. That Moses is his, that Abraham is his,
that Torah is his, right? That he is in succession to that even though he's a Greek and not a Jew
or against Judaism. So, Judaism and Christianity...
are still in it. I mean, we're taught, we're just talking about the latter half of the second
century. Right, right. So they're still in close proximity in dialogue in polemic in argument
in apologetics back and forth. Right. That's still going on. That's frankly still going on.
They aren't two separate religions, rabbinic Judaism as such, and Christianity as such
basically are two fully separate religious traditions around 500.
Yeah, so here's really an interesting bit that just expresses what you said from St.
Irenaeus is on page 82. All these testimonies, so this is all the things you just mentioned,
right about Jesus. Yeah. All these testimonies concerning his seed according to the flesh,
expressly make known both the race and the place where he was going to be born,
so that men might not seek among the nations or somewhere else the begotten Son of God,
except in Bethlehem of Judea of the seed of Abraham.
Ham and David. Very, very explicit, very specific. Yes. Yeah. This is it. Those promises are
fulfilled. The promise to Abraham is fulfilled in Jesus. Yeah, David is fulfilled in Jesus.
are still outstanding. Yeah. So that's still a key element.
Right this continuity
With the Old Testament is still a key element of Christianity, right?
So now
Right we come to the end of that the triumphal entry that of course leads into Christ's death
Right and in talking about Christ's death is crucifixion where he emphasizes here on this pass is that Christ's death is voluntary
And it is according to the father's will.
And he's quoting a lot of Isaiah, primarily Isaiah 53, right, which our Protestant friends
love to quote, especially those who are pushing penal substitutionary atonement, but that's
not how St. Irenaeus reads it at all.
So he reads all those things about...
God the father being pleased to crush him and these things as oh, that's just saying it's according to the father's will
Right. It isn't that somehow the enemies of God
Overcame God and killed his Messiah
Right, I mean, let's think about that for a second, right that this is all according to God's will
That's what Isaiah was saying according to St.
dear to ask, and that Christ's death is voluntary, right? They didn't overcome Christ.
either. Right? They didn't defeat Christ. Christ accepted all of these things. That's what it's
talking about. He gave his back to scourgings. What Isaiah says that he's talking about the fact
that Christ underwent this voluntarily. He died voluntarily. He makes that very explicit.
That's the importance of it. And the importance of it for him is again, obedience.
it's yeah and there's right there's I say you'll be yeah I'll just say what's
not
in here. What's not in here is any sense that God is mad and has to be pacified by killing
his own son. Or that that's just not in here. Just not in here.
Or any sense of substitution. Yeah, any sense that Christ suffers so you don't have to.
Or Christ is obedient so you don't have to be quite the opposite. Right. Remember,
He reveals the knowledge of good.
He reveals the way that leads to life
Those who follow his path are saved from death are saved from hell actually from Hades at one point. He says
Right and and to really emphasize this there's a particular passage
in this context where a
Bunch of people if they were reading it now, you know, like if reading it if they're going out and quote mining and trying to find quote
to support penal substitutionary atonement right they'd start reading this one and get
kind of excited right because he talks about oh there there are those who uh take judgment
upon themselves right and those who have judgment taken away right saturday starts talking that
way and and you can tell a certain type of person be like oh see he's gonna do penal
substitution he's gonna say christ took the punishment so it was taken away from us christ
I just took the judge with some...
let's take it away from us. But no. Sorry, guys. What St.
Ernest ends up saying is that those who killed Christ, those
who opposed Christ, take judgment upon themselves. And those
who follow Christ in obedience have their judgment taken
away. Yep. Nothing about
Christ
Taking punishment or judgment on himself
So that we don't have to sorry guys
And then he runs through a
whole bunch of Old Testament quotes
that if you've read the Passion Narratives or
Listen to our Passion Narratives episode a couple months ago
Will be really familiar right all of the thing they parted my garments among them in for my clothes
they cast lots. All of the things that are quoted in the gospels and the narratives of
Christ's passion, St. Irenaeus runs through and also quotes about Christ's death, but again,
without referencing the New Testament texts, he just quotes the Old Testament texts and talks
about how they're fulfilled in Christ. He's following the New Testament as a model,
not just parroting it or sighting it.
Then he talks about the way of life, the law, the Torah, and the commandments, and he talks
about how the law has been fully encompassed by love.
That's the language I'm using because he quotes, this is the closest thing to quoting
St. Paul, where St. Paul in Roman says, uh, that, uh, he who loves keeps the whole law.
He kind of asserts the same thing, but then what he quotes is he says Christ said and then he quotes Deuteronomy, right?
Love the Lord your God. Love your neighbor's yourself. He gives the Old Testament quotes
But again the idea is not
Okay, throw all the commandments of the Torah in the dustbin. We just have to you know love God and love each other
It's something
sense, right? Because he's very explicit. He actually works this
out in the text, St. Irenaeus does. He points out, right? Like,
if you love, if you love God, and you love your neighbor, you
will not commit adultery. Like he runs through actual
commandments from the Torah, and shows how if you are
loving, if you are doing this, if you are practicing
God's love.
then
You will keep all of those commandments. So it's not that those commandments are now irrelevant. It's that if you love you'll keep them all
Right, which you still need to do
I mean it says over and over again in the scriptures if you love me you keep my commandments if you you know like it
Loving God and keeping his commandments are just I
Don't know how there's dozens dozens of pairings in the scriptures old and New Testament. It's just the way it is
and he re-emphasizes what is also the emphasis
of the New Testament.
He does the same thing,
but he quotes the Old Testament passages.
The New Covenant is where the law,
the Torah is written on your heart.
So again, this emphasis that through Christ's sacrifice,
now, and the coming of the Holy Spirit into our heart,
now we are able to love.
We have been shown the good.
We have received the knowledge of the good, right?
And we're now able to practice this
and work this out.
And in the same way, he then,
because he's still talking about this new covenant,
talks about Israel being reconstituted,
the people of God being reconstituted from the nations.
Right?
And he even does the exact move that St. Paul does.
He explicitly says that Israel, right?
Israel is Christ, right?
Recapitulation again, and therefore,
if you are...
in Christ, you are in Israel, right? When he's talking about the nations. So again, it's not
Israel's done away with, or Israel's replaced, or right? It's, if you're in Christ, you're in Israel.
And if you're not, you're not. And so then he kind of concludes with, right? He's summarizing,
okay, so all this that we've laid out.
This is, and he uses two phrases, this is the preaching of the truth and this is the way of life
that we've received from Christ through the apostles. And those two things are not separate.
Right. The revelation of the truth and the preaching of the truth
is not separate from living the way of life.
God has set before us and so that's
There's the contents and you can go and read it and get a lot more detail but of on the Apostolic preaching indeed
Yeah, I you know in in wrapping up this episode. I think
I
Think that you know we talked about this a little bit at the beginning
But I would really just want to underline what the title of this work means on the app select preach
In other words, for Irenaeus, this is essentially the contents of the Gospel, right?
Obviously it's much more elaborate, relatively speaking, than simply saying, this is who Jesus
is, what he accomplished, and what he expects of everyone.
But that is what this book is about.
That's what's in this book.
He just goes on about it a lot more and goes through the scriptures to describe it.
Um
There's a few things I want to say about that, like so for him, for instance, you know, stuff
like the Tower of Babel and even the Giant Lore, this is part of the Gospel for Irenaeus.
This is part of the message.
I'm not saying that every time the Gospel is preached it has to include that specific
content, but he's writing a treatise here, right?
He aims to set out the whole of the apostolic preaching and that's what this book is.
And that's one of the reasons that I say that if this is all the theology...
you have maybe in addition to the scriptures, you're doing well.
I'm not saying you don't need anything else, but you're doing very, very well.
So the other thing I wanted to point out, so I just had these couple of short observations.
The other thing I wanted to point out is something I've mentioned a lot as we've gone
on throughout this episode, and that is that if you read it, if you read this book
And you are a c-
And by that, I don't just mean you went to the classes, I mean that you absorbed the
teaching, you're living the life.
And you read this, you're like, oh, this is my faith.
This is what I believe, this is what I practice, this is what we're doing.
And I think that's a really important thing to point out because as we've talked about
a number of times on this show. A lot of people have this idea of a kind of evolution.
evolutionary view of the scriptures, evolutionary view of the teaching of the church, the idea
that there's this more primitive version earlier and then it becomes something bigger
or different later, develops into a different kind of doctrine.
If you really familiarize yourself with just the second century texts of the church, just
those fathers, right? So we're not even
talking about getting into the Cappadocians, we're not talking about the Ecumenical Councils,
none of that stuff. Just second century, this period where the church is still very persecuted.
If you just read this stuff like Irenaeus, Justin Martyr, you know, Apostolic Fathers
Ignatius of Antioch, these texts, you're going to simply see the Orthodox faith
as it is. So this
This idea that people sometimes have, like, oh, you know, it's changed a lot over the
years.
Okay, there are certain ways in which the church has changed, for sure.
Ways things are expressed, ways things that are applied or whatever.
But you will see the whole Orthodox faith, the whole Orthodox faith in the church fathers
of the second century.
And so, if you see that, number one, if you're an Orthodox Christian, it should
lead you to be.
Very confident that the faith you practice, the faith that you believe, the faith that
you were taught is the same faith from 2,000 years ago.
But also if you're not an Orthodox Christian, maybe you reject some of what Irenaeus says
here or Justin Martyr or whoever else, then you have to deal with the fact that your
understanding of the New Testament is radically different from the understanding of the New
a testament that was held by the people that were one or maybe two.
maybe three generations later. And you're going to have to come up with an explanation
for how that could be. From an Orthodox point of view, we're just saying, well, they're
simply like Uranus reading the scriptures, understanding the faith of what it means
to be Christian the same way that the apostles did. I mean, you could be like a Mormon
and say, well, you know, went off the deep end
pretty much right away.
Okay.
then you're going to have to have a reason why your way of it not being off the deep end is
the way, why your restored version, your recovered version is the way. I think it's more reasonable
to conclude that the church did not completely fail within the death of the last apostle,
or maybe even earlier. I think it's much more reasonable to believe that the church,
You know maintained the faith that the apostles were not
losers and failures that they succeeded in bringing the true Christian faith to those who were listening to them and then that the men
that they chose to be the next generation of church leaders the bishops and the presbyters and the deacons
That they passed on what they received
faithfully
So yeah, I think your nace is fascinating and then and we've talked about and I hope that we do
some more second-century stuff, so
No promises.
father Stephen wants to throw something out here at the end, but we'll see. You know, send
off in the chat. I'll be interested to hear what you guys think. Would you like some more
second century stuff? I think there's a lot of great stuff to read. So, yeah, that's that's
what I have to say about it. Yeah, so I think the thing that is really impressed me again
is that the modern era has really complicated Christianity.
And here's what I mean by that.
Our Protestant friends, one of their core doctrines is the perspicuity of Scripture.
The idea that the main and the important things, the things you really need to know as a Christian
are clear from just you sitting down and reading the Bible.
even though this may get clipped.
context. I think they actually have a point. I think that's actually kind of
true in a certain way, but I think it ends up cutting against the whole
Protestant project. Here's what I mean by that. I think the average person,
actually, if they sit down and read, say Matthew's Gospel say, Sermon on the
Mount, I think they can kind of get it.
St. John's gospel is a little harder, right? But St. Luke's gospel
Even most of St. John's gospel they can they can kind of get the point if they just read it
I mean, it's it's actually kind of clear on the face
and
What's the understanding you get well, I need to I need to go to Christ Church. I need to be baptized. I need to
Save the Eucharist I need to live out my life. I need to take care of my family take care of my community
to care my friends. I need to love other people. I need to show that love by doing good in the world for them.
I need to, when I sin, and I am going to sin, when I sin, I need to repent of that sin before God and I need to
do everything I can to make that right with the people I've sinned against.
And when I get to the end of my life, I need to face the end of my life
my life with confidence and trust in Christ as my Savior.
And in the resurrection of the dead, I think you can get that now, which was just by reading
the Bible.
But see, then all this other stuff comes in, right of, well, no, no, actually, okay.
So look, so there's, there's this thing justification and justification is where you're declared
innocent before God because you're guilty before God because of something Adam did
thousands of years ago.
And so you're going to go to hell.
That's gonna punish you with eternal torment because
of what Adam did thousands of years ago and so because of that you're going to hell but don't
worry Christ took that punishment if you believe in him and by that we mean believe certain things
and there's certain things that are non-negotiable certain things are negotiable but then you're
justified and but you can't do anything to get justified but then after that you're
sanctified and you do do things to get sanctified and so and now it's really confusing.
And all of these distinctions are held to be like super important like you're whether you go to heaven or hell when you die hinges on you
figuring this out and
Keeping all these distinctions correct and then all of this stuff
right and
You don't get any of all that stuff from just sitting down and reading the Bible
I'm sorry. You just don't
You don't
no one ever has. Martin Luther did not just sit down and objectively read the
Bible for the first time in Greek. He had personal issues. There were issues in the
Church of his day, the Roman Catholic Church of his day, right? There were
problems. He lived in a society, right? He had a cultural background, all that
colored with.
read. He read it in terms of those things and how it addressed those things. Same thing
with Calvin. You don't get any of this stuff from that.
So I think what has occurred to me as we're reading St. Irenaeus is on the Apostolic preaching
because it's refreshingly simple. What is St. Irenaeus' vision of Christianity? You
come to the church, you get baptized, you come and worship and receive the Eucharist.
You
life, you strive to love and by loving you keep the commandments of God, you
follow in the path that Christ tread, you find salvation from death. All those
things are just talking about. It's very simple and you don't have to get all up
in your head about it. You don't have to get all worked up about it. You don't have to
have a bunch of arguments about it. What we actually need to do is just
very clear and simple.
I think we need to be careful to the orthodox folks listening.
I think we need to be careful when we're presenting Christ Church, orthodox Christianity, the original
Christianity to people, that we don't overcomplicate it.
Essence energy's distinction is true.
It's theologically important.
You cannot know anything about it and live a Christian
life and become a saint and find salvation. I'm obviously a big theology nerd. I know a
lot of stuff. A lot of the stuff I know isn't strictly speaking relevant. We need to just
present the faith as Scripture presents it, as St. Irenaeus presents it. This is what
most people need. This is what most people are looking for. They want to go deeper into
this or that or the other. They want to understand this or that or the other.
Cool! But that's all after the fact, right? That's all after the fact.
What people need to hear is that the way your life is now is not the way it needs
to be. There's another way to live. There's another way to be in the world.
That way has been opened up to us by our Lord Jesus Christ. Here's who He is.
Then here's where you can come to an Orthodox church near you.
to start walking that path and start following him really straightforward,
really simple. Studeronomy says it's in your mouth and on your heart.
It's not far from you.
All of us can do it if we decide we want to.
So those are my final thoughts. Amen. Amen. Well,
thanks for tuning in everybody. Uh,
but the generators running up there in Chesterton. Uh, it's been, uh,
It's been a great great covers. I'm kind of disappointed. We didn't have a constant
In the background from the generators. Well, they weren't running, you know, the mics are also there in Chesterton
So yeah, anyway, if you didn't happen to get through to us live everybody
We'd like to hear from you. Anyways, you can email us at lordofspiritsonancientfaith.com
You can message us at our Facebook page. You can leave us a voicemail speakpipe.com slash lord of spirits
And if you have basic questions about orthodox Christianity or you need help to find a parish in the 3d world
world, go to orthodoxintro.
And finally, be sure to go to ancientfaith.com, stroke support, and help make sure we and
lots of other AFR podcasters stay on the air.
Crazy, scary, spooky, hilarious.
Thank you.
Good night.
And may God bless you all through the prayers of seniorness.
You've been listening to the Lord of Spirits with Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew
Stephen Daimack and Father Stephen DeYoung, a listener-supported presentation of ancient
faith radio.
And I beheld, and I heard the voice of many angels round about the throne and the beasts
and the elders.
And the number of them was 10,000 times 10,000 than thousands of thousands, saying
with a loud voice.
worthy is the land that was slain to receive power and riches and wisdom and
strength and honor and glory and blessing.
Revelation chapter 5 verses 11 through 12